<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /Users/cindy/tmp/grobid-0.6.1/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Higher-order organization of complex networks</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016-12-26">26 Dec 2016</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Austin</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Benson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Institute for Computational and Mathematical Engineering</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">Stanford University</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Purdue University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Gleich</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jure</forename><surname>Leskovec</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Computer Science Department</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Stanford University</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Higher-order organization of complex networks</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2016-12-26">26 Dec 2016</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1612.08447v1[cs.SI]</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.1" ident="GROBID" when="2021-01-31T12:43+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
				<p>Networks are a fundamental tool for understanding and modeling complex systems in physics, biology, neuroscience, engineering, and social science. Many networks are known to exhibit rich, lower-order connectivity patterns that can be captured at the level of individual nodes and edges. However, higher-order organization of complex networks-at the level of small network subgraphsremains largely unknown. Here we develop a generalized framework for clustering networks based on higher-order connectivity patterns. This framework provides mathematical guarantees on the optimality of obtained clusters and scales to networks with billions of edges. The framework reveals higher-order organization in a number of networks including information propagation units in neuronal networks and hub structure in transportation networks. Results show that networks exhibit rich higher-order organizational structures that are exposed by clustering based on higher-order connectivity patterns.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Networks are a standard representation of data throughout the sciences, and higher-order connectivity patterns are essential to understanding the fundamental structures that control and mediate the behavior of many complex systems <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b2">(3)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b3">(4)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b4">(5)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">(6)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>. The most common higher-order structures are small network subgraphs, which we refer to as network motifs ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Figure 1A</ref>). Network motifs are considered building blocks for complex networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b7">8)</ref>. For example, feedforward loops ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Figure 1A</ref>  Here we use higher-order network structures to gain new insights into the organization of complex systems. We develop a framework that identifies clusters of network motifs. For each network motif ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Figure 1A)</ref>, a different higher-order clustering may be revealed ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Figure 1B</ref>), which means that different organizational patterns are exposed depending on the chosen motif.</p><p>Conceptually, given a network motif M , our framework searches for a cluster of nodes S with two goals. First, the nodes in S should participate in many instances of M . Second, the set S should avoid cutting instances of M , which occurs when only a subset of the nodes from a motif are in the set S ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Figure 1B</ref>). More precisely, given a motif M , the higher-order clustering framework aims to find a cluster (defined by a set of nodes S) that minimizes the following ratio:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">φ M (S) = cut M (S,S)/ min(vol M (S), vol M (S)),<label>(1)</label></formula><p>whereS denotes the remainder of the nodes (the complement of S), cut M (S,S) is the number of instances of motif M with at least one node in S and one inS, and vol M (S) is the number of nodes in instances of M that reside in S. Equation 1 is a generalization of the conductance metric in spectral graph theory, one of the most useful graph partitioning scores <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>. We refer to φ M (S) as the motif conductance of S with respect to M .</p><p>Finding the exact set of nodes S that minimizes the motif conductance is computationally infeasible <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">(12)</ref>. To approximately minimize Equation 1 and hence identify higher-order clusters, we develop an optimization framework that provably finds near-optimal clusters (Supplementary Materials <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>). We extend the spectral graph clustering methodology, which is based on the eigenvalues and eigenvectors of matrices associated with the graph <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">(11)</ref>, to account for higher-order structures in networks. The resulting method maintains the properties of traditional spectral graph clustering: computational efficiency, ease of implementation, and mathematical guarantees on the near-optimality of obtained clusters. Specifically, the clusters identified by our higher-order clustering framework satisfy the motif Cheeger inequality <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(14)</ref>, which means that our optimization framework finds clusters that are at most a quadratic factor away from optimal.</p><p>The algorithm (illustrated in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Figure 1C</ref>) efficiently identifies a cluster of nodes S as follows:</p><p>•</p><p>Step 1: Given a network and a motif M of interest, form the motif adjacency matrix W M whose entries (i, j) are the co-occurrence counts of nodes i and j in the motif M :</p><p>(W M ) ij = number of instances of M that contain nodes i and j.</p><p>•</p><p>Step 2: Compute the spectral ordering σ of the nodes from the normalized motif Laplacian matrix constructed via W M (15).</p><p>•</p><p>Step 3: Find the prefix set of σ with the smallest motif conductance, formally: S := arg min r φ M (S r ), where S r = {σ 1 , . . . , σ r }.</p><p>For triangular motifs, the algorithm scales to networks with billions of edges and typically only takes several hours to process graphs of such size. On smaller networks with hundreds of thousands of edges, the algorithm can process motifs up to size 9 (13). While the worstcase computational complexity of the algorithm for triangular motifs is Θ(m <ref type="bibr">1.5</ref> ) , where m is the number of edges in the network, in practice the algorithm is much faster. By analyzing real-world networks where the number of edges m ranges from 159,000 to 2 billion we found the computational complexity to scale as Θ(m <ref type="bibr">1.2</ref> ). Moreover, the algorithm can easily be parallelized and sampling techniques can be used to further improve performance <ref type="bibr" target="#b16">(16)</ref>.</p><p>The framework can be applied to directed, undirected, and weighted networks as well as motifs <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>. Moreover, it can also be applied to networks with positive and negative signs on the edges, which are common in social networks (friend vs. foe or trust vs. distrust edges) and metabolic networks (edges signifying activation vs. inhibition) <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>. The framework can be used to identify higher-order structure in networks where domain knowledge suggests the motif of interest. In the Supplementary Material <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref> we also show that when domain-specific higherorder pattern is not known in advance, the framework can also serve to identify which motifs are important for the modular organization of a given network <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>. Such a general framework allows for a study of complex higher-order organizational structures in a number of different networks using individual motifs and sets of motifs. The framework and mathematical theory immediately extend to other spectral methods such as localized algorithms that find clusters around a seed node <ref type="bibr" target="#b17">(17)</ref> and algorithms for finding overlapping clusters <ref type="bibr" target="#b18">(18)</ref>. To find several clusters, one can use embeddings from multiple eigenvectors and k-means clustering <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b19">19)</ref> or apply recursive bi-partitioning <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b20">20)</ref>.</p><p>The framework can serve to identify higher-order modular organization of networks. We apply the higher-order clustering framework to the C. elegans neuronal network, where the fournode "bi-fan" motif ( <ref type="figure">Figure 2A</ref>) is over-expressed <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>. The higher-order clustering framework then reveals the organization of the motif within the C. elegans neuronal network. We find a cluster of 20 neurons in the frontal section with low bi-fan motif conductance ( <ref type="figure">Figure 2B</ref>).</p><p>The cluster shows a way that nictation is controlled. Within the cluster, ring motor neurons (RMEL/V/R), proposed pioneers of the nerve ring <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(21)</ref>, propagate information to IL2 neurons, regulators of nictation <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(22)</ref>, through the neuron RIH and several inner labial sensory neurons ( <ref type="figure">Figure 2C</ref>). Our framework contextualizes the sifnifance of the bi-fan motif in this control mechanism.</p><p>The framework also provides new insights into network organization beyond the clustering of nodes based only on edges. Results on a transportation reachability network <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(23)</ref> demonstrate how it finds the essential hub interconnection airports ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3</ref>). These appear as extrema on the primary spectral direction ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3C</ref>) when two-hop motifs ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3A</ref> For example, Atlanta, a large hub, is embedded next to Salina, a non-hub, with an edge-based method ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure 3D</ref>).</p><p>Our higher-order network clustering framework unifies motif analysis and network partitioningtwo fundamental tools in network science-and reveals new organizational patterns and modules in complex systems. Prior efforts along these lines do not provide worst-case performance guarantees on the obtained clustering <ref type="bibr" target="#b24">(24)</ref>, do not reveal which motifs organize the network <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(25)</ref>, or rely on expanding the size of the network <ref type="bibr" target="#b26">(26,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b27">27)</ref>. Theoretical results in the Supplementary Material (13) also explain why classes of hypergraph partitioning methods are more general than previously assumed and how motif-based clustering provides a rigorous framework for the special case of partitioning directed graphs. Finally, the higher-order net-work clustering framework is generally applicable to a wide range of networks types, including directed, undirected, weighted, and signed networks.</p><p>A B C <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Figure 1</ref>: Higher-order network structures and the higher-order network clustering framework. A: Higher-order structures are captured by network motifs. For example, all 13 connected three-node directed motifs are shown here. B: Clustering of a network based on motif M 7 . For a given motif M , our framework aims to find a set of nodes S that minimizes motif conductance, φ M (S), which we define as the ratio of the number of motifs cut (filled triangles cut) to the minimum number of nodes in instances of the motif in either S orS <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>. In this case, there is one motif cut. C: The higher-order network clustering framework. Given a graph and a motif of interest (in this case, M 7 ), the framework forms a motif adjacency matrix (W M ) by counting the number of times two nodes co-occur in an instance of the motif. An eigenvector of a Laplacian transformation of the motif adjacency matrix is then computed. The ordering σ of the nodes provided by the components of the eigenvector (15) produces nested sets S r = {σ 1 , . . . , σ r } of increasing size r. We prove that the set S r with the smallest motif-based conductance, φ M (S r ), is a near-optimal higher-order cluster (13).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 2:</head><p>Higher-order cluster in the C. elegans neuronal network <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(28)</ref>. A: The 4-node "bi-fan" motif, which is over-expressed in neuronal networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>. Intuitively, this motif describes a cooperative propagation of information from the nodes on the left to the nodes on the right. B: The best higher-order cluster in the C. elegans frontal neuronal network based on the motif in (A). The cluster contains three ring motor neurons (RMEL/V/R; cyan) with many outgoing connections, serving as the source of information; six inner labial sensory neurons (IL2DL/VR/R/DR/VL; orange) with many incoming connections, serving as the destination of information; and four URA neurons (purple) acting as intermediaries. These RME neurons have been proposed as pioneers for the nerve ring <ref type="bibr" target="#b21">(21)</ref>, while the IL2 neurons are known regulators of nictation <ref type="bibr" target="#b22">(22)</ref>, and the higher-order cluster exposes their organization. The cluster also reveals that RIH serves as a critical intermediary of information processing. This neuron has incoming links from all three RME neurons, outgoing connections to five of the six IL2 neurons, and the largest total number of connections of any neuron in the cluster. C: Illustration of the higher-order cluster in the context of the entire network. Node locations are the true twodimensional spatial embedding of the neurons. Most information flows from left to right, and we see that RME/V/R/L and RIH serve as sources of information to the neurons on the right.  <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(23)</ref>. A: The three higher-order structures used in our analysis. Each motif is "anchored" by the blue nodes i and j, which means our framework only seeks to cluster together the blue nodes. Specifically, the motif adjacency matrix adds weight to the (i, j) edge based on the number of third intermediary nodes (green squares). The first two motifs correspond to highly-connected cities and the motif on the right connects non-hubs to non-hubs. B: The top 50 most populous cities in the United States which correspond to nodes in the network. The edge thickness is proportional to the weight in the motif adjacency matrix W M . The thick, dark lines indicate that large weights correspond to popular mainline routes. C: Embedding of nodes provided by their corresponding components of the first two non-trivial eigenvectors of the normalized Laplacian for W M . The marked cities are eight large U.S. hubs (green), three West coast non-hubs (red), and three East coast non-hubs (purple). The primary spectral coordinate (left to right) reveals how much of a hub the city is, and the second spectral coordinate (top to bottom) captures West-East geography <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">(13)</ref>. D: Embedding of nodes provided by their corresponding components in the first two non-trivial eigenvectors of the standard, edge-based (non-higher-order) normalized Laplacian. This method does not capture the hub and geography found by the higher-order method. For example, Atlanta, the largest hub, is in the center of the embedding, next to Salina, a non-hub.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S1 Derivation and analysis of the motif-based spectral clustering method</head><p>We now cover the background and theory for deriving and understanding the method presented in the main text. We will start by reviewing the graph Laplacian and cut and volume measures for sets of vertices in a graph. We then define network motifs in Section S1.2 and generalizes the notions of cut and volume to motifs. Our new theory is presented in Section S1.6 and then we summarize some extensions of the method. Finally, we relate our method to existing methods for directed graph clustering and hypergraph partitioning.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S1.1 Review of the graph Laplacian for weighted, undirected graphs</head><p>Consider a weighted, undirected graph G = (V, E), with |V | = n. Further assume that G has no isolated nodes. Let W encode the weights, of the graph, i.e., W ij = W ji = weight of edge (i, j).</p><p>The diagonal degree matrix D is defined as D ii = n j=1 W ij , and the graph Laplacian is defined as L = D − W . We now relate these matrices to the conductance of a set S, φ (G) (S):</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">φ (G) (S) = cut (G) (S,S)/ min(vol (G) (S), vol (G) (S)),<label>(S3)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">cut (G) (S,S) = i∈S, j∈S W ij ,<label>(S4)</label></formula><p>vol <ref type="bibr">(G)</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_4">(S) = i∈S D ii (S5)</formula><p>Here,S = V \S. (Note that conductance is a symmetric measure in S andS, i.e., φ (G) (S) = φ (G) (S).) Conceptually, the cut and volume measures are defined as follows: cut (G) (S,S) = weighted sum of weights of edges that are cut (S6) vol (G) (S) = weighted number of edge end points in S (S7)</p><p>Since we have assumed G has no isolated nodes, vol (G) (S) &gt; 0. If G is disconnected, then for any connected component C, φ (G) (C) = 0. Thus, we usually consider breaking G into S10 connected components as a pre-processing step for algorithms that try to find low-conductance sets.</p><p>We now relate the cut metric to a quadratic form on L. Later, we will derive a similar form for a motif cut measure. Note that for any vector y ∈ R n ,</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">y T Ly = (i,j)∈E w ij (y i − y j ) 2 .<label>(S8)</label></formula><p>Now, define x to be an indicator vector for a set of nodes S i.e., x i = if node i is in S and</p><p>x i = 0 if node i is inS. Note that if an edge (i, j) is cut, then x i and x j take different values</p><p>and</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">(x i − x j ) 2 = 1; otherwise, (x i − x j ) 2 = 0. Thus, x T Lx = cut (G) (S,S). (S9)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S1.2 Definition of network motifs</head><p>We now define network motifs as used in our work. We note that there are alternative definitions in the literature <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>. We consider motifs to be a pattern of edges on a small number of nodes (see <ref type="figure">Figure S4</ref>). Formally, we define a motif on k nodes by a tuple (B, A), where B is a k × k binary matrix and A ⊂ {1, 2, . . . , k} is a set of anchor nodes. The matrix B encodes the edge pattern between the k nodes, and A labels a relevant subset of nodes for defining motif conductance.</p><p>In many cases, A is the entire set of nodes. Let χ A be a selection function that takes the subset of a k-tuple indexed by A, and let set(•) be the operator that takes an (ordered) tuple to an (unordered) set. Specifically,</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">set((v 1 , v 2 , . . . , v k )) = {v 1 , v 2 , . . . , v k }.</formula><p>The set of motifs in an unweighted (possibly directed) graph with adjacency matrix A, denoted <ref type="figure">Figure S4</ref>: A: Illustration of network motifs used throughout the main text and supplementary material. The motif M edge is used to represent equivalence to undirected the graph. B: Diagram of motif definitions. The motif is defined by a binary matrix B and an anchor set of nodes. The figure shows an anchored version of motif M 2 with anchors on the nodes that form the bi-directional edge. There are two instances of the motif in the graph on the right. Note that ({a, b, d}, {a, b}) is not included in the set of motif instances because the induced subgraph on the nodes a, b, and d is not isomorphic to the graph defined by B.</p><p>where A v is the k × k adjacency matrix on the subgraph induced by the k nodes of the ordered vector v. <ref type="figure">Figure S4</ref> illustrates these definitions. The set operator is a convenient way to avoid duplicates when defining M (B, A) for motifs exhibiting symmetries. Henceforth, we will just</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">use (v, χ A (v)) to denote (set(v), set(χ A (v))) when discussing elements of M (B, A). Further- more, we call any (v, χ A (v)) ∈ M (B, A)</formula><p>a motif instance. When B and A are arbitrary or clear from context, we will simply denote the motif set by M .</p><p>We call motifs where χ A (v) = v simple motifs and motifs where χ A (v) = v anchored motifs. Motif analysis in the literature has mostly analyzed simple motifs <ref type="bibr" target="#b29">(29)</ref>. However, the anchored motif provides us with a more general framework, and we use an anchored motif for S12 the analysis of the transportation reachability network.</p><p>Often, a distinction is made between a functional and a structural motif (30) (or a subgraph and an induced subgraph (31)) to distinguish whether a motif specifies simply the existence of a set of edges (functional motif or subgraph) or the existence and non-existence of edges (structural motif or induced subgraph). By the definition in Equation S10, we refer to structural motifs in this work. Note that functional motifs consist of a set of structural motifs. Our clustering framework allows for the simultaneous consideration of several motifs (see Section S1.9), so we have not lost any generality in our definitions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S1.3 Definition of motif conductance</head><p>Recall that the key definitions for defining conductance are the notions of cut and volume. For an unweighted graph, these are</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">φ (G) (S,S) = cut (G) (S,S)/ min(vol (G) (S), vol (G) (S)),<label>(S11)</label></formula><p>cut (G) (S,S) = number of edges cut, (S12) vol (G) (S) = number of edge end points in S. (S13)</p><p>Our conceptual definition of motif conductance simply replaces an edge with a motif instance of type M : We say that a motif instance is cut if there is at least one anchor node in S and at least one S13 anchor node inS. We can formalize this when given a motif set M as in Equation S10:</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">φ (G) M (S) = cut (G) M (S,S)/ min(vol (G) M (S), vol (G) M (S)),<label>(S14)</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_11">cut (G) M (S,S) = (v,χ A (v))∈M 1(∃ i, j ∈ χ A (v) | i ∈ S, j ∈S), (S17) vol (G) M (S) = (v,χ A (v))∈M i∈χ A (v) 1(i ∈ S),<label>(S18)</label></formula><p>where 1(s) is the truth-value indicator function on s, i.e., 1(s) takes the value 1 if the statement s is true and 0 otherwise. Note that Equation S17 makes explicit use of the anchor set A. The motif cut measure only counts an instance of a motif as cut if the anchor nodes are separated, and the motif volume counts the number of anchored nodes in the set. However, two nodes in an achor set may a part of several motif instances. Specifically, following the definition in Equation S10, there may be many different v with the same χ A (v), and the nodes in χ A (v) still get counted proportional to the number of motif instances.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S1.4 Definition of the motif adjacency matrix and motif Laplacian</head><p>Given an unweighted, directed graph and a motif set M , we conceptually define the motif adjacency matrix by (W M ) ij = number of motif instances in M where i and j participate in the motif.</p><p>Or, formally,</p><formula xml:id="formula_13">(W M ) ij = (v,χ A (v))∈M 1({i, j} ⊂ χ A (v)),<label>(S20)</label></formula><p>for i = j. Note that weight is added to (W M ) ij only if i and j appear in the anchor set. This is important for the transportation reachability network analyzed in the main text and in Section S6, where weight is added between cities i and j based on the number of intermediary cities that can be traversed between them.</p><p>Next, we define the motif diagonal degree matrix by</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">(D M ) ii = n j=1 (W M ) ij and the motif Laplacian as L M = D M − W M . Finally, the normalized motif Laplacian is L M = S14 D −1/2 M L M D −1/2 M = I − D −1/2 M W M D −1/2 M .</formula><p>The theory in the next section will examine quadratic forms L M and derive the main clustering method that uses an eigenvector of L M .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S1.5 Algorithm for finding a single cluster</head><p>We are now ready to describe the algorithm for finding a single cluster in a graph. The algorithm finds a partition of the nodes into S andS. The motif conductance is symmetric in the sense </p><formula xml:id="formula_15">that φ (G) M (S) = φ (G) M (S),</formula><formula xml:id="formula_16">G M ← weighted graph induced W M D M ← diagonal matrix with (D M ) ii = j (W M ) ij z ← eigenvector of second smallest eigenvalue for L M = I − D −1/2 M W M D −1/2 M σ i ← to be index of D −1/2 M z with ith smallest value / * Sweep over all prefixes of σ * / S ← arg min l φ (G M ) (S l ), where S l = {σ 1 , . . . , σ l } if |S| &lt; |S| then return S else returnS</formula><p>It is often informative to look at all conductance values found from the sweep procedure.</p><p>We refer to a plot of φ (G M ) (S l ) versus l as a sweep profile plot. In the following subection, we</p><p>show that when the motif has three nodes,</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">φ (G M ) (S l ) = φ (G) M (S l )</formula><p>. In this case, the sweep profile shows how motif conductance varies with the size of the sets in Algorithm 1.</p><p>In the following subsection, we show that when the motif M has three nodes, the cluster An implementation of Algorithm 1 is available in SNAP. See http://snap.stanford.edu/ higher-order/.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S15</head><formula xml:id="formula_18">satisfies φ (G) M (S) ≤ 4 √ φ *</formula><p>, where φ * is the smallest motif conductance over all sets of nodes. In other words, the cluster is nearly optimal. Later, we extend this algorithm to allow for signed, colored, and weighted motifs and to simultaneously finding multiple clusters.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S1.6 Motif Cheeger inequality for network motifs with three nodes</head><p>We now derive the motif Cheeger inequality for simple three-node motifs, or, in general, motifs with three anchor nodes. The crux of this result is deriving a relationship between the motif conductance function and the weighted motif adjacency matrix, from which the Cheeger inequality is essentially a corollary. For the rest of this section, we will use the following notation. Given an unweighted, directed G and a motif M , the corresponding weighted graph defined by Equation S20 is denoted by G M .</p><p>The following Lemma relates the motif volume to the volume in the weighted graph. This lemma applies to any anchor set A consisting of at least two nodes. For our main result, we will apply the lemma assuming |A| = 3. However, we will apply the lemma more generally when discussing four node motifs in Section S1.7.</p><p>Lemma 1. Let G = (V, E) be a directed, unweighted graph and let G M be the weighted graph for a motif on k nodes and |A| ≥ 2 anchor nodes. Then for any <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure S5</ref>: Illustrations of the quadratic forms on indicator functions for set assignment. Here, the blue nodes have assignment to set S and the green nodes have assignment to setS. The quadratic function gives the penalty for cutting that motif. A: Illustration of Equation S21. The quadratic form is proportional to the indicator on whether or not the motif is cut. B: Illustration of Equation S22. The quadratic form is equal to zero when all nodes are in the same set. However, the form penalizes 2/2 splits more than 3/1 splits.</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">S ⊂ V , vol (G) M (S) = 1 |A| − 1 vol (G M ) (S) Proof. Consider an instance (v, χ A (v)) of a motif. Let (u 1 , . . . , u |A| ) = χ A (v). By Equa- tion S20, (W M ) u 1 ,j is incremented by one for j = u 2 , . . . , u |A| . Since (D M ) u 1 ,u 1 = j (W M ) u 1 ,j , the motif end point u 1 is counted |A| − 1 times. S16 x i 2 + x j 2 + x k 2 -x i x j -x j x k -x k x i = x i = 1 x j = 1 x k = 1 i j k x i = -1 x j = -1 x k = -1 i j k x i = 1 x j = 1 x k = -1 i j k x i = 1 x j = -1 x k = -1 i j k 0 0 4 4 i i k j l x j = 1 x k = 1 x i = 1 x l = 1 i i k j l x j = -1 x k = -1 x i = -1 x l = -1 i i k j l x j = 1 x k = -1 x i = 1 x l = 1 i i k j l x j = -1 x k = -1 x i = 1 x l = -1 i i k j l x j = 1 x k = -1 x i = 1 x l = -1 0 0 6 6 8 6 -x i x j -x i x k -x i x l -x j x k -x j x l -x k x l = B A</formula><p>The following lemma states that the truth value for determining whether three binary variables in {−1, 1} are not all equal is a quadratic function of the variables (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure S5</ref>). Because this function is quadratic, we will be able to relate motif cuts on three nodes to a quadratic form on the motif Laplacian.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S17</head><formula xml:id="formula_20">Lemma 2. Let x i , x j , x k ∈ {−1, 1}. Then 4 • 1(x i , x j , x k not all the same) = x 2 i + x 2 j + x 2 k − x i x j − x j x k − x k x i .</formula><p>It will be easier to derive our results with binary indicator variables taking values in {−1, 1}.</p><p>However </p><formula xml:id="formula_21">x i = 1 if z i = 1 and x i = −1 if z i = 0. Then for any graph Laplacian L = D − W , 4z T Lz = x T Lx.</formula><p>Proof.</p><p>x</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">T Lx = (i,j)∈E W ij (x i − x j ) 2 = (i,j)∈E W ij 4(z i − z j ) 2 = 4z T Lz.</formula><p>The next lemma contains the essential result that relates motif cuts in the original graph G to weighted edge cuts in G M . In particular, the lemma shows that the motif cut measure is proportional to the cut on the weighted graph defined in Equation S19 when there are three anchor nodes.</p><p>Lemma 4. Let G = (V, E) be a directed, unweighted graph and let G M be the weighted graph for a motif with |A| = 3. Then for any</p><formula xml:id="formula_23">S ⊂ V , cut (G) M (S,S) = 1 cut (G M ) (S,S) S18</formula><p>Proof. Let x ∈ {−1, 1} n be an indicator vector of the node set S.</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">4 • cut (G) M (S,S) = (v,{i,j,k})∈M 4 • 1(x i , x j , x k not all the same) = (v,{i,j,k})∈M x 2 i + x 2 j + x 2 k − (x i x j + x j x k + x k x i ) = 1 2 x T D M x − 1 x T W M x = 1 2 x T L M x = 2 • cut (G M ) (S,S).</formula><p>The first equality follows from the definition of cut motifs (Equation S17). The second equality follows from Lemma 2. The third equality follows from Lemma 1 and Equation S20. The fourth equality follows from the definition of L M . The fifth equality follows from Lemma 3.</p><p>We are now ready to prove our main result, namely that motif conductance on the original graph G is equivalent to conductance on the weighted graph G M when there are three anchor nodes. The result is a consequence of the volume and cut relationships provided by Lemmas 1 and 4.</p><p>Theorem 5. Let G = (V, E) be a directed, unweighted graph and let W M be the weighted adjacency matrix for any motif with |A| = 3. Then for any</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">S ⊂ V , φ (G) M (S) = φ (G M ) (S)</formula><p>In other words, when the number of anchor nodes is 3, the motif conductance is equal to the conductance on the weighted graph defined by Equation S19.</p><p>Proof. When |A| = 3, the motif cut and motif volume are both equal to half the motif cut and motif volume measures by Lemmas 1 and 4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S19</head><p>For any motif with three anchor nodes, conductance on the weighted graph is equal to the motif conductance. Because of this, we can use results from spectral graph theory for weighted graphs <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(32)</ref> and re-interpret the results in terms of motif conductance. In particular, we get the following "motif Cheeger inequality".</p><p>Theorem 6. Motif Cheeger Inequality. Suppose we use Algorithm 1 to find a low-motif con-</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">ductance set S. Let φ * = min S φ (G)</formula><p>M (S ) be the optimal motif conductance over any set of nodes</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">S . Then 1. φ (G) M (S) ≤ 4 √ φ * and 2. φ * ≥ λ 2 /2</formula><p>Proof. The result follows from Theorem and the standard Cheeger ineqaulity <ref type="bibr" target="#b32">(32)</ref>.</p><p>The first part of the result says that the set of nodes S is within a quadratic factor of optimal.</p><p>This provides the mathematical guarantees that our procedure finds a good cluster in a graph, if one exists. The second result provides a lower bound on the optimal motif conductance in terms of the eigenvalue. We use this bound in our analysis of a food web (see Section S7.1) to</p><p>show that certain motifs do not provide good clusters, regardless of the procedure to select S.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S1.7 Discussion of motif Cheeger inequality for network motifs with four or more nodes</head><p>Analogs of the indicator function in Lemma 2 for four or more variables are not quadratic.</p><p>Subsequently, for motifs with |A| &gt; 3, we no longer get the motif Cheeger inequalities guaranteed by Theorem 6. That being said, solutions found by motif-based partitioning approximate a related value of conductance. We now provide the details.</p><p>We begin with a lemma that shows a functional form for four binary variables taking values in {−1, 1} to not all be equal. We see that it is quartic, not quadratic. S20</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">Lemma 7. Let x i , x j , x k , x l ∈ {−1, 1}.</formula><p>Then the indicator function on all four elements not being equal is</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">8 • 1(x i , x j , x k , x l not all the same) (S21) = (7 − x i x j − x i x k − x i x l − x j x k − x j x l − x k x l − x i x j x k x l ) .</formula><p>We almost have a quadratic form, if not for the quartic term</p><formula xml:id="formula_30">x i x j x k x l .</formula><p>However, we could use the following related quadratic form:</p><formula xml:id="formula_31">6 − x i x j − x i x k − x i x l − x j x k − x j x l − x k x l =    0 x i , x j , x k , x l are all the same 6 exactly three of x i , x j , x k , x l are the same 8 exactly two of x i , x j , x k , x l are −1. (S22)</formula><p>The quadratic still takes value 0 if all four entries are the same, and takes a non-zero value otherwise. However, the quadratic takes a larger value if exactly two of the entries are −1. </p><formula xml:id="formula_32">S ⊂ V , cut (G) M (S,S) = 1 cut (G M ) (S,S) − (v,{i,j,k,l})∈M 1 • 1(exactly two of i, j, k, l in S) S21</formula><p>Proof. Let x ∈ {−1, 1} n be an indicator vector of the node set S.</p><p>• cut</p><formula xml:id="formula_33">(G) M (S,S) + (v,{i,j,k,l})∈M 2 • 1(exactly two of i, j, k, l in S) = (v,{i,j,k,l})∈M 6 − x i x j − x i x k − x i x l − x j x k − x j x l − x k x l = (v,{i,j,k,l})∈M 3 2 x 2 i + x 2 j + x 2 k + x 2 l − (x i x j + x i x k + x i x l + x j x k + x j x l + x k x l ) = 1 2 x T D M x − 1 x T W M x = 1 2 x T L M x = 2 • cut (G M ) (S,S).</formula><p>The first equality follows from Equations S17 and S22. The third equality follows from Lemma 1.</p><p>The fourth equality follows from the definition of L M . The fifth equality follows from Lemma 3.</p><p>With four anchor nodes, the motif cut in G is slightly different than the weighted cut in the weighted graph G M . However, Lemma 1 says that the motif volume in G is still the same as the weighted volume in G M . We use this to derive the following result.</p><p>Theorem 9. Let G = (V, E) be a directed, unweighted graph and let W M be the weighted adjacency matrix for any motif with |A| = 4. Then for any</p><formula xml:id="formula_34">S ⊂ V , φ (G) M (S) = φ (G M ) (S) − (v,{i,j,k,l})∈M 1(exactly two of i, j, k, l in S) vol (G M ) (S)</formula><p>In other words, when there are four anchor nodes, the weighting scheme in Equation S19 models the exact conductance with an additional penalty for splitting the four anchor nodes into two groups of two.</p><p>Proof. This follows from Lemmas 1 and 8.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S22</head><p>To summarize, we still get a Cheeger inequality from the weighted graph, but it is in terms of a penalized version of the motif conductance φ</p><formula xml:id="formula_35">(G)</formula><p>M (S). However, the penalty makes sense-if the group of four nodes is "more split" (2 and 2 as opposed to 3 and 1), the penalty is larger.</p><p>When |A| &gt; 4, we can derive similar penalized approximations to φ</p><formula xml:id="formula_36">(G) M (S).</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S1.8 Methods for simultaneously finding multiple clusters</head><p>For clustering a network into k &gt; 2 clusters based on motifs, we could recursively cut the graph using the sweep procedure with some stopping criterion <ref type="bibr" target="#b20">(20)</ref>. For example, we could continue to cut the largest remaining cluster until the graph is partitioned into some pre-specified number of clusters. We refer to this method as recursive bi-partitioning.</p><p>In addition, we can use the following method of Ng et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b19">(19)</ref>. Algorithm 2: Motif-based clustering algorithm for finding several clusters.</p><p>Input:</p><formula xml:id="formula_37">Directed, unweighted graph G, motif M , number of clusters k Output: k disjoint motif-based clusters (W M ) ij ← number of instances of M that contain nodes i and j. D M ← diagonal matrix with (D M ) ii = j (W M ) ij z 1 , . . . , z k ← eigenvectors of k smallest eigenvalues for L M = I − D −1/2 M W M D −1/2 M Y ij ← z ij / k j=1 z 2 ij</formula><p>Embed node i into R k by taking the ith row of the matrix Y Run k-means clustering on the embedded nodes This method does not have the same Cheeger-like guarantee on quality. However, recent theory shows that by replacing k-means with a different clustering algorithm, there is a performance guarantee <ref type="bibr" target="#b33">(33)</ref>. While this provides motivation, we use k-means for its simplicity and empirical success.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S1.9 Extensions of the method for simultaneously analyzing several network motifs</head><p>All of our results carry through when considering several motifs simultaneously. In particular, suppose we are interested in clustering based on motif sets M 1 , . . . , M q for q different motifs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S23</head><p>Further suppose that we want to weight the impact of some motifs more than other motifs. Let W M j be the weighted adjacency matrix for motif M j , j = 1, . . . , q, and let α j ≥ 0 be the weight of motif M j , then we can form the weighted adjacency matrix</p><formula xml:id="formula_38">W M = q j=1 α j W M j .<label>(S23)</label></formula><p>Now, the cut and volume measures are simply weighted sums by linearity. Suppose that the M j all have three anchor nodes and let G M be the weighted graph corresponding to W M . Then</p><formula xml:id="formula_39">cut (G M ) (S,S) = q j=1 α j cut (G) M j (S,S), vol (G M ) (S) = q j=1 α j vol (G) M j (S),</formula><p>and Theorem 6 applies to a weighted motif conductance equal to</p><formula xml:id="formula_40">q j=1 α j cut (G) M j (S,S) min q j=1 α j vol (G) M j (S), q j=1 α j vol (G) M j (S)</formula><p>. S1.10 Extensions of the method to signed, colored, and weighted motifs</p><p>Our results easily generalize for signed networks. We only have to generalize Equation S10 by allowing the adjacency matrix B to be signed. Extending the method for motifs where the edges or nodes are "colored" or "labeled" is similar. If the edges are colored, then we again just allow the adjacency matrix B to capture this information. If the nodes in the motif are colored, we only count motif instances with the specified pattern.</p><p>We can also generalize the notions of motif cut and motif volume for "weighted motifs", i.e., each motif has an associated nonnegative weight. Let ω (v,χ A (v)) be the weight of a motif instance. Our cut and volume metrics are then</p><formula xml:id="formula_41">cut (G) M (S,S) = (v,χ A (v))∈M ω (v,χ A (v)) 1(∃ i, j ∈ χ A (v) | i ∈ S, j ∈S), vol (G) M (S) = (v,χ A (v))∈M ω (v,χ A (v)) i∈χ A (v) 1(i ∈ S).</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S24</head><p>Subsequently, we adjust the motif adjacency matrix as follows: </p><formula xml:id="formula_42">(W M ) ij = (v,χ A (v))∈M ω (v,χ A (v)) 1({i, j} ⊂ χ A (v))<label>(S24</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_43">B 1 = 0 1 0 0 , B 2 = 0 1 1 0 ,</formula><p>where both motifs are simple (A = {1, 2}). If W 1 and W 2 are the motif adjacency matrices for B 1 and B 2 , then A + A T = W = W 1 + 2W 2 . This weighting scheme gives a weight of two to bi-directional edges in the original graph and a weight of one to uni-directional edges.</p><p>An alternative strategy for clustering a directed graph is to simply remove the direction on all edges, treating bi-directional and uni-directional edges the same. The resulting adjacency matrix is equivalent to the motif adjacency matrix for the bi-directional and uni-directional edges (without any relative weighting). Formally, W = W 1 + W 2 . We refer to this "motif" as M edge ( <ref type="figure">Figure S4</ref>), which will later provide a convenient notation when discussing both motifbased clustering and edge-based clustering.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S25</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S1.12 Connections to hypergraph partitioning</head><p>Finally, we contextualize our method in the context of existing literature on hypergraph partitioning. The problem of partitioning a graph based on relationships between more than two nodes has been studied in hypergraph partitioning <ref type="formula">37</ref>, and we can interpret motifs as hyperedges in a graph. In contrast to existing hypergraph partitioning problems, we induce the hyperedges from motifs rather than take the hyperedges as given a priori. The goal with our analysis of the Florida Bay food web, for example, was to find which hyperedge sets (induced by a motif) provide a good clustering of the network (see Section S7.1).</p><p>In general, our motif-based spectral clustering methodology falls into the area of encoding a hypergraph partitioning problem by a graph partitioning problem <ref type="bibr" target="#b38">(38,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b39">39)</ref>. Specifically, it respects the standard cut and volume metrics for graph partitioning.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S2 Computational complexity and scalability of the method</head><p>We now analyze the computation of the higher-order clustering method. We first provide a theoretical analysis of the computational complexity, which depends on motif. After, we empirically analyze the time to find clusters for triangular motifs on a variety of real-world networks, ranging in size from a few hundred thousand edges to nearly two billion edges. Finally, we</p><p>show that we can practically compute the motif adjacency matrix for motifs up to size 9 on a number of real-world networks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S26</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S2.1 Analysis of computational complexity</head><p>We now analyze the computational complexity of the algorithm presented in Theorem 6. Overall, the complexity of the algorithm is governed by the computations of the motif adjacency matrix W M , an eigenvector, and the sweep cut procedure. For simplicity, we assume that we (3) for every triangle in G undir , check which directed triangle motif it is in G. Since step 1 is linear and we can perform the check in step 3 in O(1) time, the same Θ(m  We note that we could also employ approximation algorithms to estimate the weights in the motif adjacency matrix <ref type="bibr" target="#b52">(52)</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S2.2 Experimental results on triangular motifs</head><p>In this section, we demonstrate that our method scales to real-world networks with billions of edges. We tested the scalability of our method on 16 large directed graphs from a variety of real-world applications. These networks range from a couple hundred thousand to two billion edges and from 10 thousand to over 50 million nodes. After computing the eigenvector, we sort the vertices and loop over prefix sets to find the lowest motif conductance set. We consider these final steps as part of the eigenvector computation for our performance experiments.</p><p>For each network in <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table S1</ref>, we ran the method for all directed triangular motifs (M 1 -</p><formula xml:id="formula_44">M 7 )</formula><p>. To compute W M , we used a standard algorithm that meets the O(m 3/2 ) bound <ref type="bibr" target="#b47">(47,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b51">51)</ref> with some additional pre-processing based on the motif. Specifically, the algorithm is:</p><p>1. Take motif type M and graph G as input. is not included in the time. The regression coefficient for log(m) (a in Equation S25) was found to be smaller 1.5 for each motif <ref type="table">(Table S3</ref>). The largest regression coefficient was 1.31</p><p>for M 3 (with 95% confidence interval 1.31 ± 0.19). We also performed a regression over the aggregate times of the motifs, and the regression coefficient was 1.17 (with 95% confidence interval 1.17 ± 0.09). We conclude that on real-world datasets, the algorithm for computing W M performs much better than the worst-case guarantees.   <ref type="table">Table S3</ref>: The 95% confidence interval (CI) for the regression coefficient of the regressor log(m) in a linear model for predicting the time to compute W M , based on the computational results for the networks in <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table S1</ref>. The algorithm runs is guranteed to run in time O(m 3/2 ). "Combined" refers to the regression coefficient when considering all of the times. </p><formula xml:id="formula_45">Motif M 1 M 2 M 3 M 4 M 5 M 6 M</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S33</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S2.3 Experimental results on k-cliques</head><p>On smaller graphs, we can compute larger motifs. To illustrate the computation time, we formed the motif adjacency matrix W based on the k-cliques motif for k = 4, . . . , 9. We implemented the k-clique enumeration algorithm by Chiba and Nishizeki with the additional pre-processing of computing the (k − 1)-core of the graph. (This pre-processing improves the running time in practice but does not affect the asymptotic complexity.) The motif adjacency matrices for k-cliques are sparser than the adjacency matrix of the original graph. Thus, we do not worry about spatial complexity for these motifs.</p><p>We ran the algorithm on nine real-world networks, ranging from roughly four thousande nodes and 88 thousand edges to over two million nodes and around five million edges (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">Table S4</ref>.) Each network contained at least one 9-clique and hence at least one k-clique for k &lt; 9. All networks were downloaded from the SNAP collection at http://snap.stanford.</p><p>edu/data/ (56). All computations ran on the same server as for the triangular motifs and again there was no parallelism. We terminated computations after two hours. For five of the nine networks, the time to compute W M for the k-clique motif was under two hours for k = 4, . . . , 9 <ref type="table">(Table S5</ref>). And for each network, the computation finished within two hours for k = 4, 5, 6.</p><p>The smallest network (in terms of number of nodes and number of edges) was the Facebook ego network, where it took just under two hours to comptue W M for the 6-clique motif and over two hours for the 7-clique motif. This network has around 80,000 edges. On the other hand, for the YouTube network, which contains nearly 3 million edges, we could compute W M for the 9-clique motif in under a minute.</p><p>We conclude that it is possible to use our frameworks with motifs much larger than the three-node motifs on which we performed many of our experiments. However, the number of edges is not that correlated with the running time to compute W M . This makes sense becuse the Chiba and Nishizeki algorithm complexity is O(a k−2 m), where a is the arboricity of the graph.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S34</head><p>Hence, the dependence on the number of edges is always linear. </p><formula xml:id="formula_46">, M 2 , M 3 , M 4 , M 5 , M 6 ,</formula><p>and M 7 (see <ref type="figure">Figure S4</ref>) in terms of the matrices U and B. The central computational kernel in these computations is (X • Y ) • Z. When X, Y , and Z are sparse, efficient parallel algorithms have been developed and analyzed <ref type="bibr" target="#b61">(61)</ref>. If the adjacency matrix is sparse, then computing W M for these motifs falls into this framework. <ref type="table">Table S6</ref>: Matrix-based formulations of the weighted motif adjacency matrix W M (Equation S19) for all triangular three-node simple motifs. P • Q denotes the Hadamard (entry-wise) products of matrices P and Q. If A is the adjacency matrix of a directed, unweighted graph G, then B = A • A T and U = A − B. Note that in all cases, W M is symmetric.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Motif</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Matrix computations</head><formula xml:id="formula_47">W M = M 1 C = (U • U ) • U T C + C T M 2 C = (B • U ) • U T + (U • B) • U T + (U • U ) • B C + C T M 3 C = (B • B) • U + (B • U ) • B + (U • B) • B C + C T M 4 C = (B • B) • B C M 5 C = (U • U ) • U + (U • U T ) • U + (U T • U ) • U C + C T M 6 C = (U • B) • U + (B • U T ) • U T + (U T • U ) • B C M 7 C = (U T • B) • U T + (B • U ) • U + (U • U T ) • B C</formula><p>With these matrix formulations, implementing the motif-based spectral partitioning algorithm for modestly sized graphs is straightforward. However, these computations become slower than standard fast triangle enumeration algorithms when the networks are large and sparse. Nevertheless, the matrix formulations provide a simple and elegant computational </p><formula xml:id="formula_48">= 1(j ∈ χ A (v i )). Then S37 (W M ) ij = (A T M A M ) ij , i = j. (S26)</formula><p>This provides a convenient algebraic formulation for defining the weighted motif adjacency matrix. However, in practice, we do not use this formulation for any computations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S4 Alternative clustering algorithms for evaluation</head><p>For our experiments, we compare our spectral motif-based custering to the following methods:</p><p>• Standard, edge-based spectral clustering, which is a special case of motif-based clustering. In particular, the motifs</p><formula xml:id="formula_49">B 1 = 0 1 1 0 , B 2 = 0 1 0 0 , A = {1, 2}<label>(S27)</label></formula><p>correspond to removing directionality from a directed graph. We refer to the union of these two motifs as M edge .</p><p>• Infomap, which is based on the map equation <ref type="bibr" target="#b62">(62)</ref>. Software for Infomap was downloaded from http://mapequation.org/code.html. We run the algorithm the algorithm for directed links when the network under consideration is directed.</p><p>• The Louvain method <ref type="bibr" target="#b63">(63)</ref>. Software for the Louvain method was downloaded from https://perso.uclouvain.be/vincent.blondel/research/louvain.</p><p>html We use the "oriented" version of the Louvain method for directed graphs. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S5.1 Connected components of the motif adjacency matrices</head><p>We again first onsider the connected components of the motif adjacency matrices as a pre- </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S5.2 Comparison of bi-fan motif cluster to clusters found by existing methods</head><p>We  For the subsequent analysis, we consider the set with the largest number of overlapping nodes with S bifan . Call these sets S M 8 and S edge . We also consider the cluster found by Infomap and the Louvain method with the largest overlap with S bifan . Call these sets S I and S L .</p><p>To compare the most similar clusters found by other methods to S bifan , we look at two metrics. First, how many neurons in S bifan are in a cluster found by existing methods (in other S40 words, the overlap). A cluster consisting of all nodes in the graph would trivially have 100% overlap with S bifan but loses all precision in the cluster identification. Thus, we also consider the sizes of the clusters. These metrics are summarized as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_50">|S bifan ∩ S M 8 | = 20, |S M 8 | = 68</formula><p>|S bifan ∩ S edge | = 20,</p><formula xml:id="formula_51">|S</formula><formula xml:id="formula_52">edge | = 64 |S bifan ∩ S L | = 13, |S L | = 27 |S bifan ∩ S I | = 19, |S I | = 114</formula><p>We see that S bifan is a subset of S M 8 and S edge and has substantial overlap with S I . However, S bifan is by far the smallest of all of these sets. We conclude that existing methods do not capture the same information as motif M bifan .</p><p>To further investigate the structure found by existing methods, we show the clusters S edge and S M 8 in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">Figure S8</ref>. From the figure, we see that spectral clustering based on edges or motif M 8 simply finds a spatially coherent cluster, rather than the control structure formed by the nodes in S bifan . </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S41</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S6.1 Methods for spectral embeddings</head><p>We compared the motif-based spectral embedding of the transportation reachability network to spectral embeddings from other connectivity matrices. For this analysis, we ignore the travel times times and only consider the topology of the network. The two-dimensional spectral embedding for a graph defined by a (weighted) adjacency matrix W ∈ R n×n comes from Algorithm 2:</p><formula xml:id="formula_53">1. Form the normalized Laplacian L = I − D −1/2 W D −1/2 , where D is the diagonal degree matrix with D ii = j W ij .</formula><p>2. Compute the first 3 eigenvectors z 1 , z 2 , z 3 of smallest eigenvalues for L (z 1 has the smallest eigenvalue).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Form the normalized matrix</head><formula xml:id="formula_54">Y ∈ R n×3 by Y ij = z ij / 3 j=1 z 2 ij . S43</formula><p>4. Define the primary and secondary spectral coordinates of node i to be Y i2 and Y i3 , respectively.</p><p>We consider the following three matrices W .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Motif:</head><p>The sum of the motif adjacency matrix (Equation S20) for three different anchored motifs:</p><formula xml:id="formula_55">B 1 =   0 1 1 1 0 1 1 1 0   , B 2 =   0 1 1 1 0 1 0 1 0   , B 3 =   0 1 0 1 0 1 0 1 0   , A = {1, 3}. (S28)</formula><p>If S is the matrix of bidirectional links in the graph (S ij = 1 if and only if A ij = A ji = 1),</p><p>then the motif adjacency matrix for these motifs is W M = S 2 . The resulting embedding is shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 4C</ref> of the main text.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Undirected:</head><p>The adjacency matrix is formed by ignoring edge direction. This is the standard spectral embedding. The resulting embedding is shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 4D</ref> of the main text.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Undirected complement:</head><p>The adjacency matrix is formed by taking the complement of the undirected adjacency matrix. This matrix tends to connect non-hubs to each other.</p><p>The networks represented by each adjacency matrices are all connected.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S6.2 Comparison of motif-based embedding to other embeddings</head><p>We computed 99% confidence intervals for the Pearson correlation of the primary spectral coordinate with the metropolitan population of the city using the Pearson correlation coefficient. <ref type="table" target="#tab_11">Table S7</ref> lists the confidence intervals. (Since eigenvectors are only unique up to sign, the confidence intervals are symmetric about 0. We list the interval with the largest positive end point S44 under this permutation to be consistent across embeddings.) The motif-based primary spectral coordinate has the strongest correlation with the city populations.</p><p>We repeated the computations for the correlation between the secondary spectral coordinate and the longitude of the city. Again, the motif-based clustering has the strongest correlation.</p><p>Furthermore, the lower end of the confidence interval for the motif-based embedding was above the higher end of the confidence interval for the other three embeddings.</p><p>Finally, in order to visualize these relationships, we computed Loess regressions of city metropolitan population and longitude against the primary and secondary spectral coordinates for each of the embeddings ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_14">Figure S9</ref>). The sign of the eigenvector used in each regression was chosen to match correlation shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figures 3C and 3D</ref> in the main text (primary spectral coordinate positively correlated with population and secondary spectral coordinate negatively correlated with longitude). The Loess regressions visualize the stronger correlation of the motifbased spectral coordinates with the metropolitan popuatlion and longitude.</p><p>We conclude that the embedding provided by the motif adjacency matrix more strongly captures the hub nature of airports and West-East geography of the network. To gain further insight into the relationship of the primary spectral coordinate's relationship with the hub airports, we visualize the adjacency matrix in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_15">Figure S10</ref>, where the nodes are ordered by the spectral ordering. We see a clear relationship between the spectral ordering and the connectivity.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S7.1 Motif M 6 in the Florida Bay food web</head><p>We now apply the higher-order clustering framework on the Florida Bay ecosystem food web <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">(64)</ref>.</p><p>The dataset was downloaded from http://vlado.fmf.uni-lj.si/pub/networks/ data/bio/foodweb/Florida.paj. In this network, the nodes are compartments (roughly, organisms and species) and the edges represent directed carbon exchange (in many cases, this means that species j eats species i). Motifs model energy flow patterns between several species.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S7.1.1 Identifying higher-order modular organization</head><p>In this case study, we use the framework to identify higher-order modular organization of networks. We focus on three motifs: M 5 corresponds to a hierarchical flow of energy where species i and j are energy sources (prey) for species k, and i is also an energy source for j; M 6 models two species that prey on each other and then compete to feed on a common third species; and M 8 describes a single species serving as an energy source for two non-interacting species. Motif M 5 is considered a building block for food webs <ref type="bibr" target="#b65">(65,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b66">66)</ref>, and the prevalence of motif M 6 is predicted by a certain niche model <ref type="bibr" target="#b67">(67)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S47</head><p>The framework reveals that low motif conductance (high-quality) clusters only exist for motif M 6 (motif conductance 0.12), whereas clusters based on motifs M 5 or M 8 have high motif conductance (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Figure S11)</ref>. In fact, the motif Cheeger inequality <ref type="table">(Theorem 6)</ref>  </p><formula xml:id="formula_56">φ M 6 (H M 6 , C) ≤ min min S φ M 5 (H M 5 , S), min S φ M 8 (H M 8 , S) .<label>(S29)</label></formula><p>This means that, in terms of motif conductance, any cluster based on motifs M 5 or M 8 is worse than the cluser found by the algorithm in Theorem 6 for motif M 6 . We note that the same conclusions hold for edge-based clustering. For motif M edge , the lower bound on conductance was 0.2194 and the cluster found by the algorithm had conductance 0.4083.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S7.1.2 Analysis of higher-order modular organization</head><p>Subsequently, we used motif M 6 to cluster the food web, revealing four clusters ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Figure S11</ref>).</p><p>Three represent well-known aquatic layers: (i) the pelagic system; (ii) the benthic predators of eels, toadfish, and crabs; (iii) the sea-floor ecosystem of macroinvertebrates. The fourth</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S48</head><p>cluster identifies microfauna supported by particulate organic carbon in water and free bacteria. <ref type="table">Table S9</ref> lists the nodes in each cluster.</p><p>We also measured how well the motif-based clusters correlate to known ground truth system subgroup classifications of the nodes <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">(64)</ref>. These classes are microbial, zooplankton, and sediment organism microfauna; detritus; pelagic, demersal, and benthic fishes; demseral, seagrass, and algae producers; and macroinvertebrates <ref type="table">(Table S9</ref>). <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">2</ref> We also consider a set of labels which does not include the subclassification for microfauna and producers. In this case, the labels are microfauna; detritus; pelagic, demersal, and benthic fishes; producers; and macroinvertebrates.</p><p>To quantify how well the clusters found by motif-based clustering reflect the ground truth labels, we used several standard evaluation criteria: adjusted rand index, F1 score, normalized mutual information, and purity <ref type="bibr" target="#b69">(69)</ref>. We compared these results to the clusters of several methods using the same evaluation criteria. In total, we evaluated six methods: 4. Edge-based clustering with recursive bi-partitioning with the same partitioning process.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">The Infomap algorithm.</head><p>The classifications are also available on our project web page: http://snap.stanford.edu/ higher-order/. For the first four algorithms, we control the number of clusters, which we set to 4. For the last two algorithms, we cannot control the number of clusters. However, both methods found 4</p><p>clusters. <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table S10</ref> shows that the motif-based clustering by embedding + k-means had the best performance for each classification criterion on both classifications. We conclude that the organization of compartments in the Florida Bay foodweb are better described motif M 6 than by edges.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S7.1.3 Connected components of the motif adjacency matrices</head><p>Finally, we discuss the discuss the preprocessing step of our method, where we compute com-  <ref type="table">Table S8</ref> lists the nodes in each component. We note that the group of 12 nodes corresponds to the green cluster in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Figure S11</ref>  <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">(64)</ref>. A priori it is not clear whether the network is organized based on a given motif. For example, motifs M 5 (green) and M 8 (blue) do not reveal any higher-order organization (motif conductance has high values). However, the downward spikes of the red curve show that M 6 reveals rich higher-order modular structure <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>. Ecologically, motif M 6 corresponds to two species mutually feeding on each other and also preying on a common third species. B: Clustering of the food web based on motif M 6 . (For illustration, edges not participating in at least one instance of the motif are omitted.) The clustering reveals three known aquatic layers: pelagic fishes (yellow), benthic fishes and crabs (red), and sea-floor macroinvertebrates (blue) as well as a cluster of microfauna and detritus (green). Our framework identifies these modules with higher accuracy (61%) than existing methods (48-53%). C: A higher-order cluster (yellow nodes in (B)) shows how motif M 6 occurs in the pelagic layer. The needlefish and other pelagic fishes eat each other while several other fishes are prey for these two species. D: Another higher-order cluster (green nodes in (B)) shows how motif M 6 occurs between microorganisms. Here, several microfauna decompose into Particulate Organic Carbon in the water (water POC) but also consume water POC. Free bacteria serves as an energy source for both the microfauna and water POC. S51 <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table S10</ref>: Comparison of motif-based algorithms against other methods in finding ground truth structure in the Florida Bay food web <ref type="bibr" target="#b64">(64)</ref>. Performance for identifying the two classifications provided in <ref type="table">Table S9</ref>  For this case study, we examine the coherent feedforward loop motif (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Figure S12</ref>), which act as sign-sensitive delay elements in transcriptional regulation networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9)</ref>. Formally, the  These motifs have the same edge pattern and only differ in sign. All of the motifs are simple (A = {1, 2, 3}). For our analysis, we consider all coherent feedforward loops that are subgraphs on the induced subgraph of any three nodes. However, there is only one instance where the coherent feedforward loop itself is a subgraph but not an induced subgraph on three nodes.</p><p>Specifically, the induced subgraph by DAL80, GAT1, and GLN3 contains a bi-directional edge between DAL80 and GAT1, unidirectional edges from DAL80 and GAT1 to GLN3. consisting of more than one node is listed in Table S11.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S7.2.1 Connected components of the adjacency matrices</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S55</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S7.2.2 Comparison against existing methods</head><p>We note that, although the original network is connected, the motif adjacency matrix corresponds to a disconnected graph. This already reveals much of the structure in the network ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Figure S12</ref>). Indeed, this "shattering" of the graph into components for the feedforward loop has previously been observed in transcriptional regulation networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b70">(70)</ref>. We additionally used The functionalities may be downloaded from our project web page: http://snap.stanford.edu/ higher-order/. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S57</head><p>Figure S12: Higher-order organization of the S. cerevisiae transcriptional regulation network. A: The four higher-order structures used by our higher-order clustering method, which can model signed motifs. These are coherent feedfoward loop motifs, which act as sign-sensitive delay elements in transcriptional regulation networks <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">(2)</ref>. The edge signs refer to activation (positive) or repression (negative). B: Six higher-order clusters revealed by the motifs in (A). Clusters show functional modules consisting of several motifs (coherent feedforward loops), which were previously studied individually <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>. The higher-order clustering framework identifies the functional modules with higher accuracy (97%) than existing methods (68-82%). C-D: Two higher-order clusters from (B). In these clusters, all edges have positive sign. The functionality of the motifs in the modules correspond to drug resistance (C) or cell cycle and mating type match (D). The clustering suggests that coherent feedforward loops function together as a single processing unit rather than as independent elements. S58 <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table S12</ref>: Classification of coherent feedforward loop motifs by several clustering methods. In a given motif instance, we say that it is coherently labeled if the nodes comprising the motif are in the same cluster. If a motif is not coherently labeled, a "-1" is listed. The accuracy is the rand index on the labels and motif functionality on coherently labeled motifs, multiplied by the fraction of coherently labeled motifs. and 101.31 million edges, where an edge from node i to node j means that there is a hyperlink from the ith article to the jth article. The network data was downloaded from http://law. di.unimi.it/webdata/enwiki-2013/.</p><p>We used Algorithm 1 to find a motif-based cluster for motif M 6 and M edge (the algorithm was run on the largest connected component of the motif adjacency matrix). The clusters are shown in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure S13</ref>. The nodes in the motif-based cluster are cities and barangays (small S59 administrative divisions) in the Philippines. The cluster has a set of nodes with many outgoing links that form the source node in motif M 6 . In total, the cluster consists of 22 nodes and 338</p><p>edges. The linking pattern appears anomalous and suggests that perhaps the pages uplinking should receive reciprocated links. On the other hand, the edge-based cluster is much larger cluster and does not have too much structure. The cluster consists of several high-degree nodes and their neighbors. S60 <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Figure S13</ref>: Clusters from the English Wikipedia hyperlink network <ref type="bibr" target="#b57">(57)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(58)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">(59)</ref>. A-C: Motifbased cluster (A) for motif M 6 (B). The cluster consists of cities and small administrative divisions in the Philippines. The green nodes have many bi-direction links with each other and many incoming links from orange nodes at the bottom of the figure. The spy plot illustrates this network structure (C). D-F: Cluster (D) for undirected edges (E). The cluster has a few very high-degree nodes, as evidenced by the spy plot (F).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S61</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S7.4 Motif M 6 in the Twitter follower network</head><p>We also analyzed the complete 2010 Twitter follower graph <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(58,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">59,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">71)</ref>. The graph consists 41.65 million nodes (users) and 1.47 billion edges, where an edge from node i to node j signifies that user i is followed by user j on the social network. The network data was downloaded from http://law.di.unimi.it/webdata/twitter-2010/.</p><p>We used Algorithm 1 to find a motif-based cluster for motif M 6 (the algorithm was run on the largest connected component of the motif adjacency matrix). The cluster contains 151 nodes and consists of two disconnected components. Here, we consider the smaller of the two components, which consists of 38 nodes. We also found an edge-based cluster on the undirected graph (using Algorithm 1 with motif M edge ). This cluster consists of 44 nodes. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Figure S14</ref> illustrates the motif-based and edge-based clusters. Both clusters capture anomalies in the graph. The motif-based cluster consists of holding accounts for a photography company. The nodes that form bi-directional links have completed profiles (contain a profile picture) while several nodes with incomplete profiles (without a profile picture) are followed by the completed accounts. The edge-based cluster is a near clique, where the user screen names all begin with "LC ". We suspect that the similar usernames are either true social communities, holding accounts, or bots. (For the most part, their tweets are protected, so we could not verify if any of these scenarios are true). Interestingly, both M 6 and M edge find anomalous clusters.</p><p>However, their structures are quite different. We conclude that M 6 can lead to the detection of new anomalous clusters in social networks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S62</head><p>Figure S14: Clusters in the 2010 Twitter follower network <ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(58,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">59,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b71">71)</ref>. A-C: Motif-based cluster (A) for motif M 6 (B). All accounts are holding accounts for a photography company. The green nodes correspond to accounts that have completed profiles, while the orange accounts have incomplete profiles. The spy plot illustrates how the cluster is formed around this motif (C). D-F: Cluster (D) for edge-based clustering (E). The cluster consists of a near-clique (F) where all users have the prefix "LC ".</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S63</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S7.5 Motif M 7 in the Stanford web graph</head><p>The Stanford web graph <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">56)</ref> consists of 281,903 nodes and 2,312,497 edges, where an edge from node i to node j means that there is a hyperlink from the ith web page to the jth web page.</p><p>Here, all of the web pages come from the Stanford domain. The network data was downloaded from http://snap.stanford.edu/data/web-Stanford.html.</p><p>We used Algorithm 1 to find a motif-based cluster for motif M 7 , a motif that is overexpressed in web graphs <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref>. An illustration of the cluster and an edge-based cluster (i.e.,</p><p>using Algorithm 1 with M edge ) are in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure S15</ref>. Interestingly, both clusters exhibits a coreperiphery structure, albeit markedly different ones. The motif-based cluster contains several core nodes with large in-degree. Such core nodes comprise the sink node in motif M 7 . On the periphery are several clusters within which are many bi-directional links (as illustrated by the spy plot in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure S15</ref>). The nodes in these clusters then up-link to the core nodes. This type of organizational unit suggests an explanation for why motif M 7 is over-expressed: clusters of similar pages tend to uplink to more central pages. The edge-based cluster also has a few nodes with large in-degree, serving as a small core. On the periphery are the neighbors of these nodes, which themselves tend not to be connected (as illustrated by the spy plot).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S64</head><p>Figure S15: Clusters in the Stanford web graph <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7)</ref>. A-C: Motif-based cluster (A) for motif M 7 (B). The cluster has a core group of nodes with many incoming links (serving as the sink node in M 7 ; shown in orange) and several periphery groups that are tied together (the bi-directional link in M ; shown in green) and also up-link to the core. This is evident from the spy plot (C). D-F: Cluster (C) for undirected edges (B). The cluster contains a few high-degree nodes and their neighbors, and the neighbors tend to not be connected, as illustrated by the splot (F).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S65</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S7.6 Semi-cliques in collaboration networks</head><p>We used Algorithm 1 to identify clusters of a four-node motif (the semi-clique) that has been studied in conjunction with researcher productivity in collaboration networks <ref type="formula">72</ref> html. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_17">Figure S16</ref> shows the two clusters for each of the collaboration networks. In both networks, the motif-based cluster consists of a core group of nodes and similarly-sized groups on the periphery. The core group of nodes correspond to the nodes of degree 3 in the motif and the periphery group nodes correspond to the nodes of degree 2. One explanation for this organization is that there is a small small group of authors that writes papers with different research groups.</p><p>Alternatively, the co-authorship could come from a single research group, where senior authors are included on all of the papers and junior authors on a subset of the papers.</p><p>On the other hand, the edge-based clusters (i.e., </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S67</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>S8 Data availability</head><p>All data is available at our project web site at http://snap.stanford.edu/higher-order/.</p><p>The web site includes links to datasets used for experiments throughout the supplementary material <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">(7,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b56">56,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b58">(58)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b59">(59)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b60">(60)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b74">(74)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b75">(75)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b76">(76)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b77">(77)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b78">(78)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b79">(79)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b80">(80)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b81">(81)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b82">(82)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b83">(83)</ref>.</p><p>S68</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>M 5 )</head><label>5</label><figDesc>have proven fundamental to understanding transcriptional regulation networks (9), triangular motifs (Figure 1A M 1 -M 7 ) are crucial for social networks (4), open bidirectional wedges (Figure 1A M 13 ) are key to structural hubs in the brain (10), and two-hop paths (Figure 1A M 8 -M 13 ) are essential to understanding air traffic patterns (5). While network motifs have been recognized as fundamental units of networks, the higher-order organization of networks at the level of network motifs largely remains an open question.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>) are used to capture highly connected nodes and non-hubs. (The first spectral coordinate of the normalized motif Laplacian embedding was positively correlated with the airport city's metropolitan population with Pearson correlation 99% confidence interval [0.33, 0.53]). The secondary spectral direction identified the West-East geography in the North American flight network (it was negatively correlated with the airport city's longitude with Pearson correlation 99% confidence interval [-0.66, -0.50]). On the other hand, edge-based methods conflate geography and hub structure.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Higher-order spectral analysis of a network of airports in Canada and the United States</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>cutM</head><label></label><figDesc>(S) = number of motif instance end points in S. (S16)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 4 . 8 .</head><label>48</label><figDesc>S5 illustrates this idea. From this, we can provide an analogous statement to Lemma 4 for motifs with |A| = Lemma Let G = (V, E) be a directed, unweighted graph and let G M be the weighted graph for a motif with |A| = 4. Then for any</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>can access edges in a graph in O(1) time and access and modify matrix entries in O(1) time.Let m and n denote the number of edges in the graph. Theoretically, the eigenvector can be computed in O((m + n)(log n) O(1) ) time using fast Laplacian solvers<ref type="bibr" target="#b41">(41)</ref>. For the sweep cut, it takes O(n log n) to sort the indices given the eigenvector using a standard sorting algorithm such is merge sort. Computing motif conductance for each set S r in the sweep also takes linear term. In pratice, the sweep cut step takes a small fraction of the total running time of the algorithm. For the remainder of the analysis, we consider the more nuanced issue of the time to compute W M .The computational time to form W M is bounded by the time to find all instances of the motif in the graph. Naively, for a motif on k nodes, we can compute W M in Θ(n k ) time by checking each k-tuple of nodes. Furthermore, there are cases where there are Θ(n k ) motif instances in the graph, e.g., there are Θ(n 3 ) triangles in a complete graph. However, since most real-world networks are sparse, we instead focus on the complexity of algorithms in terms of the number of edges and the maximum degree in the graph. For this case, there are several efficient practical algorithms for real networks with available software<ref type="bibr" target="#b42">(42)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b43">(43)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b44">(44)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b45">(45)</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b46">(46)</ref>.Theoretically, motif counting is efficient. Here we consider four classes of motifs:<ref type="bibr" target="#b0">(1)</ref> triangles, (2) wedges (connected, non-triangle three-node motifs), (3) four-node motifs, and (4) k-cliques. Let m be the number of edges in a graph. Latapy analyzed a number of algorithms for listing all triangles in an undirected network, including an algorithm that has computational complexity Θ(m 1.5 ) (47). For a directed graph G, we can use the following algorithm: (1) form a new graph G undir by removing the direction from all edges in G (2) find all triangles in G undir , S27</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Marcus and Shavitt present an algorithm for listing all four-node motifs in an undirected graph in O(m 2 ) time<ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(49)</ref>. We can employ the same edge direction check as for triangles to extend this result to directed graphs.Chiba  and Nishizeki develop an algorithm for finding a representation of all quadrangles (motif on four nodes that contains a four-node cycle as a subgraph) in O(am) time and O(m) space, where a is the arboricity of the graph (50). The arboricity of any connected graph is bounded by O(m 1/2 ), so this algorithm runs in time O(m 3/2 ).Chiba and Nishizeki present an algorithms for k-clique enumeration that also depends on S28 the arboricity of the graph. Specifically, they provide an algorithm for enumerating all k-cliques in O(ka k−2 m) time, where a is the arboricity of the graph. This algorithm achieves the Θ(m 3/2 ) bound for arbitrary graphs. (We note that the triangle listing sub-case is similar in spirit to the algorithm proposed bySchank and Wagner (51)). For four-node cliques, the algorithm runs in time O(m 2 ) time, which matches the complexity of Marcus and Shavitt<ref type="bibr" target="#b49">(49)</ref>.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Such methods balance computation time and accuracy. Finally, we note that the computation of W M and the computation of the eigenvector are suitable for parallel computation. There are already distributed algorithms for triangle enumeration (53), and the (parallel) eigenvector computation of a sparse matrix is a classical problem in scientific computing (54, 55).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>2 . 3 . 5 . 6 .</head><label>2356</label><figDesc>(Pre-processing.) If M is M 1 or M 5 , remove all bi-directional edges in G since these motifs only contain uni-directional edges. If M is M 4 , remove all uni-directional edges in G as this motif only contains bi-directional edges. Form the undirected graph G undir by removing the direction of all edges in G. 4. Let d u be the degree of node u in G undir . Order the nodes in G undir by increasing degree, breaking ties arbitrarily. Denote this ordering by ψ. For every edge undirected edge {u, v} in G undir , if ψ u &lt; ψ v , add directed edge (u, v) to G dir ; otherwise, add directed edge (v, u) to G dir . For every node in u in G dir and every pair of directed edges (u, v) and (u, w), check to see if u, v, and w form motif M in G. If they do, check if the triangle forms motif M in G and update W M accordingly.The algorithm runs in time Θ(m 3/2 ) time in the worst case, and is also known as an effective heuristic for real-world networks<ref type="bibr" target="#b48">(48)</ref>. After, we find the largest connected component of theS30 graph corresponding to the motif adjacency matrix W M , form the motif normalized Laplacian L M of the largest component, and compute the eigenvector of second smallest eigenvalue of L M . To compute the eigenvector, we use MATLAB's eigs routine with tolerance 1e-4 and the "smallest algebraic" option for the eigenvalue type. Table S2 lists the time to compute W M and the time to compute the eigenvector for each network. We omitted the time to read the graph from disk because this time strongly depends on how the graph is compressed. All experiments ran on a 40-core server with four 2.4 GHz Intel Xeon E7-4870 processors. All computations of W M were in serial and the computations of the eigenvectors were in parallel. Over all networks and all motifs, the longest computation of W M (including pre-processing time) was for M 2 on the sk-2005 network and took roughly 52.8 hours. The longest eigenvector computation was for M 6 on the sk-2005 network, and took about 1.62 hours. We note that W M only needs to be computed once per network, regardless of the eventual number of clusters that are extracted. Also, the computation of W M can easily be accelerated by parallel computing (the enumeration of motifs can be done in parallel over nodes, for example) or by more sophisticated algorithms (48). In this work, we perform the computation of W M in serial in order to better understand the scalability. In theory, the triangle enumeration time is O(m 1.5 ). We fit a linear regression of the log of the computation time of the last step of the enumeration algorithm to the regressor log(m) and a constant term: log(time) ∼ a log(m) + b (S25) If the computations truly took cm 1.5 for some constant c, then the regression coefficient for log(m) would be 1.5. Because of the pre-processing of the algorithm, the number of edges m depends on the motif. For example, with motifs M 1 and M 5 , we only count the number of uni-directional edges. The pre-processing time, which is linear in the total number of edges, S31</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>S36 f u n</head><label></label><figDesc>c t i o n [ S , Sbar , c o n d u c t a n c e s ] = M o t i f S p e c t r a l P a r t i t i o n M 6 (A) % S p e c t r a l p a r t i t i o n i n g f o r m o t i f M B = s p o n e s (A &amp; A ' ) ; % b i d i r e c t i o n a l l i n k s U = A − B ; % u n i d i r e c t i o n a l l i n k s % Form m o t i f a d j a c e n c y m a t r i x f o r m o t i f M . % F o r d i f f e r e n t m o t i f s , r e p l a c e t h i s l i n e w i t h a n o t h e r m a t r i x f o r m u l a t i o n . W = ( B * U' ) . * U' + (U * B ) . * U + (U' * U) . * B ; % Compute e i g e n v e c t o r o f m o t i f n o r m a l i z e d L a p l a c i a n D s q r t = f u l l ( sum (W, 2 ) ) ; D s q r t ( D s q r t˜= 0 ) = 1 . / s q r t ( D s q r t ( D s q r t˜= 0 ) ) ; [ I , J , V] = f i n d (W) ; Ln = s p a r s e ( I , J , −V . * ( D s q r t ( I ) . * D s q r t ( J ) ) , s i z e (A, 1 ) , s i z e (A, 2 ) ) ; [ Z , l a m b d a s ] = e i g s ( Ln , 2 , ' s a ' ) ; % Matlab ' s e i g s i s s o m e t i m e s o u t o f o r d e r [˜, e i g o r d e r ] = s o r t ( d i a g ( l a m b d a s ) ) ; y = D s q r t . * Z ( : , e i g o r d e r ( end ) ) ; % L i n e a r t i m e sweep p r o c e d u r e [˜, o r d e r ] = s o r t ( y ) ; C = W( o r d e r , o r d e r ) ; C sums = f u l l ( sum ( C , 2 ) ) ; v o l u m e s = cumsum ( C sums ) ; v o l u m e s o t h e r = f u l l ( sum ( sum (W) ) ) * o n e s ( l e n g t h ( o r d e r ) , 1 ) − v o l u m e s ; c o n d u c t a n c e s = cumsum ( C sums − 2 * sum ( t r i l ( C ) , 2 ) ) . / min ( volumes , v o l u m e s o t h e r ) ; [˜, s p l i t ] = min ( c o n d u c t a n c e s ) ; S = o r d e r ( 1 : s p l i t ) ; S b a r = o r d e r ( ( s p l i t + 1 ) : end ) ; Figure S6: MATLAB implementation of the motif-based spectral partitioning algorithm for motif M 6 . For other motifs, line 9 can be replaced with the formulations from Table S6. method for the motif adjacency matrix W M . To demonstrate, Figure S6 provides a complete MATLAB implementation of Algorithm 1 for M 6 (Figure S4). The entire algorithm including comments comrpises 28 lines of code. An alternative matrix formulation comes from a motif-node adjacency matrix. Let M (B, A) be a motif set and number the instances of the motif 1, . . . , |M |, so that (v i , χ A (v i )) is the ith motif. Define the |M | × n motif-node adjacency matrix A M by (A M ) ij</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>processing step. For our analysis, we consider use M bifan , M 8 , and M edge (Figure S4). The original network has 131 nodes and 764 edges. The largest connected component of the motif adjacency matrix for motif M bifan contains 112 nodes. The remaining 19 nodes are isolated and correspond to the neurons AFDL, AIAR, AINR, ASGL/R, ASIL/R, ASJL/R, ASKL/R, AVL, AWAL, AWCR, RID, RMFL, SIADR, and SIBDL/R. The largest connected component of the motif adjacency matrix for motif M 8 contains 127 nodes. The remaining 4 nodes are isolated and correspond to the neurons ASJL/R and SIBDL/R. The original network is weakly connected, so the motif adjacency matrix for M edge is connected.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>found the motif-based clusters for motifs M bifan , M 8 , and M edge by running Algorithm 1 on the largest connected component of the motif adjacency matrix. Sweep profile plots (φ M (S) as S39</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure S7 :</head><label>S7</label><figDesc>Sweep profile plot (φ M (S) as a function of S from the sweep in Algorithm 1) for M bifan (green) M 8 (dark blue), and M edge (light blue). a function of S from the sweep in Algorithm 1) are shown in Figure S7 and show that the size of the M bifan returned by Algorithm 1 cluster is smaller than the clusters for M 8 and M edge . In fact, the motif-based clusters for M 8 and M edge essentially bisect the graph, containing 63 of 127 and 64 of 131 nodes, respectively. Of the 63 nodes in the M 8 -based cluster, only 2 are in the edge-based cluster, so these partitions give roughly the same information. Next, we compare the clusters found by existing methods to the M bifan -based cluster found by Algorithm 1. We will show that existing methods do not find the same group of nodes. Let S bifan be the M bifan -based cluster, which consists of 20 nodes. The nodes correspond to the following neurons: IL1DL/VL, IL2DL/DR/VL/VR/L/R, OLQDL/R, RIH, RIPL/R, RMEL/R/V, and URADL/DR/VL/VR. The partitions based on M 8 and M edge provide two sets of nodes each.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure S8 :</head><label>S8</label><figDesc>Illustration of motif-based clusters with true two-dimensional spatial dimensions of the frontal neurons of C. elegans. A: The M bifan -based cluster consists of the labeled dark blue nodes. B: Partitioning the graph based on motif M 8 , where the labeled dark blue nodes are the nodes on the side of the partition with largest overlap of the nodes in A. C: Partitioning the graph based on edges, where the labeled dark blue nodes are the nodes on the side of the partition with largest overlap of the nodes in A. Note that the partitions in Figures B and C capture the cluster inFigure A, but also contain many other nodes. Essentially, the partitions in B and C are just capturing spatial information.S42S6 Details and comparison against existing methods for the transportation reachability networkThe nodes in the transportation reachability network are airports in the United States andCanada. There is an edge from city i to city j if the estimated travel time from i to j is less than some threshold<ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(23</ref>). The network is not symmetric. The network with estimated travel times was downloaded from http://www.psi.toronto.edu/affinitypropagation/TravelRouting.mat and http://www.psi.toronto.edu/affinitypropagation/TravelRoutingCityNames. txt. We collected the latitude, longitude, and metropolitan populations of the cities using WolframAlpha and Wikipedia. All of the data is available on our project web page: http: //snap.stanford.edu/higher-order/.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>S45Figure S9 :</head><label>S9</label><figDesc>Loess regressions of city metropolitan population against the primary spectral coordinate (top) and longitude against secondary spectral coordinate (bottom) for the motif (left), undirected (middle), and undirected complement (right) adjacency matrices.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Figure S10 :</head><label>S10</label><figDesc>Visualization of transportation reachability network. Nodes are ordered by the spectral ordering provided by the motif adjacency matrix. A black dot means no edge exists in the network. For the edges in the network, lighter colors mean longer estimated travel times.S46S7 Additional case studiesWe next use motif-based clustering to analyze several additional networks. Our main goal is to show that motif-based clusters find markedly different structures in many real-world networks compared to edge-based clusters. For the case of a transcription regulation network of yeast, we also show that motif-based clustering more accurately finds known functional modules compared to existing methods. On the English Wikipedia article network and the Twitter network, we identify motifs that find anomalous clusters. On the Stanford web graph and in collaboration networks, we use motifs that have previously been studied in the literature and see how they reveal organizational structure in the networks.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>guarantees that clustering based on motif M 5 or M 8 will always have larger motif conductance that clustering based on M 6 . The inequality says that the motif conductance for any cluster in a connected motif adjacency matrix is at least half of the second smallest eigenvalue of the motif-normalized Laplacian. However, finding the cluster with optimal conductance is still computationally infeasible in general (68). The lower bounds using the largest connected component of the motif adjacency matrix for motifs M 5 , M 6 , and M 8 were 0.2195, 0.0335, and 0.2191, and the clusters found by the Algorithm 1 had motif conductances of 0.4414, 0.1200, and 0.4145. Thus, the cluster S found by the algorithm for M 6 has smaller motif M 6 -conductance (0.12) than any possible cluster's motif-M 5 or motif-M 8 conductance. To state this formally, let C be the cluster found by the algorithm for motif M 6 and let H M be the largest connected component of motif adjacency matrix for motif M . Then</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Motif-based clustering with the embedding + k-means algorithm (Algorithm 2) with 500 iterations of k-means. 2. Motif-based clustering with recursive bi-partitioning (repeated application of Algorithm 1 on the largest remaining compoennt). The process continues to cut the largest cluster until there are 4 total. 3. Edge-based clustering with the embedding + k-means algorithm, again with 500 iterations of k-means.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>S49 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>The Louvain method.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>puted connected components of the motif adjacency matrices. The original network has 128 nodes and 2106 edges. The largest connected component of the motif adjacency matrix for motif M 5 contains 127 of the 128 nodes. The node corresponding to the compartment of "roots" is the only node not in the largest connected component. The two largest connected components of the motif adjacency matrix for motif M 6 contain 12 and 50 nodes. The remaining 66 nodes are isolated.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>. The motif adjacency matrix for M 8 is connected. The original network is weakly connected, so the motif adjacency matrix for M edge is also connected. S50 Figure S11: Higher-order organization of the Florida Bay food web. A: Sweep profile plot (φ (G) M (S) as a function of S from the sweep in Algorithm 1) for different motifs on the Florida Bay ecosystem food web</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>feedforward loop is represented by the following signed motifs B 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Again, we analyze the component structure of the motif adjacency matrix as a pre-processing step. The original network consists of 690 nodes and 1082 edges, and its largest weakly connected component consists of 664 nodes and 1066 edges. Every coherent feedforward loop in the network resides in the largest weakly connected component, so we subsequently consider this sub-network in the following analysis. Of the 664 nodes in the network, only 62 participate in a coherent feedforward loop. Forming the motif adjacency matrix results in nine connected components, of sizes 18, 9, 9, 6, 6, 5, 3, 3, and 3. The operons for the connected components</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_23"><head>Algorithm 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>to partition the largest connected component of the motif adjacency matrix (consisting of 18 nodes). This revealed the cluster {CLN2, CLN1, SWI4/SWI6, SPT16, HO}, which contains three coherent feedforward loops (Figure S12). All three instances of the motif correspond to the function "cell cycle and mating type switch". The motifs in this cluster are the only feedforward loops for which the function is described in Reference<ref type="bibr" target="#b8">(9)</ref>. Using the same procedure on the undirected version of the induced subgraph of the 18 nodes (i.e., using motif M edge ) results in the cluster {CLN1, CLN2, SPT16, SWI4/SWI6 }. This cluster breaks the coherent feedforward loop formed by HO, SWI4/SWI6, and SPT16.We also evaluated our method based on the classification of motif functionality (9). In total, there are 12 different functionalities and 29 instances of labeled coherent feedforward loops. We considered the motif-based clustering of the graph to be the connected components of the motif adjacency matrix with the additional partition of the largest connected component. To form an edge-based clustering, we used the embedding + k-means algorithm on the undirected graph (i.e., motif M edge ) with k = 12 clusters. We also clustered the graph using Infomap and the Louvain method. Table S12 summarizes the results. We see that the motif-based clustering coherently labels all 29 motifs in the sense that the three nodes in every instance of a labeled motif is placed in the same cluster. The edge-based spectral, Infomap, and Louvain clustering coherently labeled 25, 23, and 23 motifs, respectively.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_24"><head>S56</head><label></label><figDesc>We measured the accuracy of each clustering method as the rand index(69)on the coherently labeled motifs, multiplied by the fraction of coherently labeled motifs. The motif-based clustering had the highest accuracy. We conclude that motif-based clustering provides an advantage over edge-based clustering methods in identifying functionalities of coherent feedforward loops in the the S. cerevisiae transcriptional regulation network.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_25"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(see Figure S16). We found a motif-based cluster in two different collaboration networks. Each one is derived from co-authorship in papers submitted to the arXiv under a certain category; here, we analyze the "High Energy Physics-Theory" (HepTh) and "Condensed Matter Physics" (Cond-Mat) categories (56,73). The HepTh network has 23,133 nodes and 93,497 edges and the Cond-Mat network has 9,877 nodes and 25,998 edges. The HepTh network data was downloaded from http://snap.stanford.edu/data/ca-HepTh.html and the CondMat network data was downloaded from http://snap.stanford.edu/data/ca-CondMat.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_26"><head>Figure S16 :</head><label>S16</label><figDesc>result of Algorithm 1 for M edge ) are a clique in the HepTh netowork and a clique with a few dangling nodes in the CondMat network. The dense clusters are quite different from the sparser clusters based on the semi-clique. Such dense clusters are not that surprising. For example, a clique could arise from a single paper published by a group of authors. S66 Clusters in co-authorship networks (73). A-E: Best motif-based cluster for the semi-clique motif (E) in the High Energy Physics-Theory collaboration network (A) and the Condensed Matter Physics collaboration network (C). Corresponding spy plots are shown in (B) and (D). F-I: Best edge-based (I) cluster in the High Energy Physics-Theory collaboration network (F) and the Condensed Matter Physics collaboration network (H). Corresponding spy plots are shown in (G) and (I).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>)</head><label></label><figDesc>S1.11 Connections to directed graph partitioningOur framework also provides a way to analyze methods for clustering directed graphs. Existing principled generalizations of undirected graph partitioning to directed graph partitioning proceed from graph circulations (34) or random walks (35) and are difficult to interpret. Our motif-based clustering framework provides a simple, rigorous framework for directed graph partitioning. For example, consider the common heuristic of clustering the symmetrized graph</figDesc><table /><note>W = A + A T , where A is the (directed) adjacency matrix (36). Following Theorem 5, conductance-minimizing methods for partitioning W are actually trying to minimize a weighted sum of motif-based conductances for the directed edge motif and the bi-directional edge motif:</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>1.5  ) complexity holds for directed networks. This analysis holds regardless of the structure of the networks. However, additional properties of the network can lead to improved algorithms. For example, in networks with a power law degree sequence with exponent greater than 7/2, Berry et al. provide a randomized algorithm with expected running time Θ(m) (48). In the case of a bounded degree graph, enumerating over all nodes and checking all pairs of neighbors takes time Θ(nd 2</figDesc><table /><note>max ), where d max is the maximum degree in the graph. We note that with triangular motifs, the number of non-zeros in W M is less than the number of non-zeros in the original adjacency matrix. Thus, we do not have to worry about additional storage requirements. Next, we consider wedges (open triangles). We can list all wedges by looking at every pair of neighbors of every node. This algorithm has Θ(nd 2 max ) computational complexity, where n is the number of nodes and d max is again the maximum degree in the graph (a more precise bound is Θ( j d 2 j ), where d j is the degree of node j.) If the graph is sparse, the motif adjacency matrix will have more non-zeros than the original adjacency matrix, so additional storage is required. Specifically, there is fill-in for all two-hop neighbors, so the motif adjacency matrix has O( j d 2 j ) non-zeros. This is impractical for large real-world networks but manageable for modestly sized networks.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table S1</head><label>S1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>lists short de- scriptions of these networks. The wiki-RfA, email-EuAll, cit-HepPh, web-NotreDame, ama- zon0601, wiki-Talk, ego-Gplus, soc-Pokec, and soc-LiveJournal1 networks were downloaded from the SNAP collection at http://snap.stanford.edu/data/ (56). The uk-2014- tpd, uk-2014-host, enwiki-2013, uk-2002, arabic-2005, twitter-2010, and sk-2005 networks were downloaded from the Laboratory for Web Algorithmics collection at http://law.di.unimi.it/datasets.php (57-60). Links to all datasets are available on our project web- site: http://snap.stanford.edu/higher-order/. Recall that Algorithm 1 consists of two major computational components: S29 1. Form the weighted graph W M .2. Compute the eigenvector z of second smallest eigenvalue of the matrix L M .</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table S1 :</head><label>S1</label><figDesc>Summary of networks used in scalability experiments with triangular motifs. The total number of edges is the sum of the number of unidirectional edges and twice the number of bidirectional edges.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Name</cell><cell>description</cell><cell># nodes</cell><cell># edges</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">total unidir. bidir.</cell></row><row><cell>wiki-RfA</cell><cell>Adminship voting on Wikipedia</cell><cell>10.8K</cell><cell cols="2">189K 175K 7.00K</cell></row><row><cell>email-EuAll</cell><cell>Emails in a research institution</cell><cell>265K</cell><cell cols="2">419K 310K 54.5K</cell></row><row><cell>cit-HepPh</cell><cell>Citations for papers on arXiv HEP-PH</cell><cell>34.5K</cell><cell>422K 420K</cell><cell>657</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">web-NotreDame Hyperlinks on nd.edu domain</cell><cell>326K</cell><cell cols="2">1.47M 711K 380K</cell></row><row><cell>amazon0601</cell><cell>Product co-purchasing on Amazon</cell><cell>403K</cell><cell cols="2">3.39M 1.50M 944K</cell></row><row><cell>wiki-Talk</cell><cell>Wikipedia users interactions</cell><cell>2.39M</cell><cell cols="2">5.02M 4.30M 362K</cell></row><row><cell>ego-Gplus</cell><cell>Circles on Google+</cell><cell>108K</cell><cell cols="2">13.7M 10.8M 1.44M</cell></row><row><cell>uk-2014-tpd</cell><cell>top private domain links on .uk web</cell><cell>1.77M</cell><cell cols="2">16.9M 13.7M 1.58M</cell></row><row><cell>soc-Pokec</cell><cell>Pokec friendships</cell><cell>1.63M</cell><cell cols="2">30.6M 14.0M 8.32M</cell></row><row><cell>uk-2014-host</cell><cell>Host links on .uk web</cell><cell>4.77M</cell><cell cols="2">46.8M 33.7M 6.55M</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">soc-LiveJournal1 LiveJournal friendships</cell><cell>4.85M</cell><cell cols="2">68.5M 17.2M 25.6M</cell></row><row><cell>enwiki-2013</cell><cell>Hyperlinks on English Wikipedia</cell><cell>4.21M</cell><cell cols="2">101M 82.6M 9.37M</cell></row><row><cell>uk-2002</cell><cell>Hyperlinks on .uk web</cell><cell>18.5M</cell><cell cols="2">292M 231M 30.5M</cell></row><row><cell>arabic-2005</cell><cell cols="2">Hyperlinks on arabic-language web pages 22.7M</cell><cell cols="2">631M 477M 77.3M</cell></row><row><cell>twitter-2010</cell><cell>Twitter followers</cell><cell>41.7M</cell><cell cols="2">1.47B 937M 266M</cell></row><row><cell>sk-2005</cell><cell>Hyperlinks on .sk web</cell><cell>50.6M</cell><cell cols="2">1.93B 1.69B 120M</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>S32</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Table S2 :</head><label>S2</label><figDesc>Time to compute the motif adjacency matrix W M and the second eigenvector of the motif normalized Laplacian L M in seconds for each directed triangular motif.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Motif adjacency matrix WM</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Second eigenvector of LM</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Network</cell><cell>M1</cell><cell>M2</cell><cell>M3</cell><cell>M4</cell><cell>M5</cell><cell>M6</cell><cell>M7</cell><cell>M1</cell><cell>M2</cell><cell>M3</cell><cell>M4</cell><cell>M5</cell><cell>M6</cell><cell>M7</cell></row><row><cell>wiki-RfA</cell><cell cols="7">1.19e+00 2.67e+00 1.71e+00 2.06e-02 1.79e+00 2.42e+00 2.35e+00</cell><cell cols="7">1.14e-01 2.12e-01 1.22e-01 2.12e-01 2.12e-01 2.94e-01 2.93e-01</cell></row><row><cell>email-EuAll</cell><cell cols="7">4.74e-01 8.29e-01 6.26e-01 2.46e-01 5.02e-01 5.40e-01 5.41e-01</cell><cell cols="7">2.29e-01 1.62e-01 2.43e-01 1.62e-01 1.62e-01 2.35e-01 1.92e-01</cell></row><row><cell>cit-HepPh</cell><cell cols="7">7.65e+00 3.36e+00 2.73e+00 6.22e+00 8.20e+00 3.29e+00 3.35e+00</cell><cell cols="7">2.11e+00 2.10e+00 2.11e+00 2.10e+00 2.10e+00 2.24e+00 2.30e+00</cell></row><row><cell cols="8">web-NotreDame 9.42e-01 2.39e+01 2.33e+01 2.30e+00 1.17e+00 8.29e+00 8.40e+00</cell><cell cols="7">1.86e-01 3.62e-01 5.97e-01 3.62e-01 3.62e-01 9.61e-01 2.06e+00</cell></row><row><cell>amazon0601</cell><cell cols="7">2.35e+00 8.66e+00 6.91e+00 1.82e+00 2.94e+00 5.47e+00 5.73e+00</cell><cell cols="7">1.23e-01 6.96e-01 4.62e+00 6.96e-01 6.96e-01 4.97e+00 4.53e+00</cell></row><row><cell>wiki-Talk</cell><cell cols="7">1.07e+01 3.00e+01 2.20e+01 3.11e+00 1.35e+01 2.09e+01 2.10e+01</cell><cell cols="7">1.28e+00 2.40e+00 2.51e+00 2.40e+00 2.40e+00 2.54e+00 4.52e+00</cell></row><row><cell>ego-Gplus</cell><cell cols="7">8.55e+02 2.42e+03 1.73e+03 2.08e+01 1.63e+03 2.07e+03 2.17e+03</cell><cell cols="7">4.42e+00 1.68e+01 2.11e+01 1.68e+01 1.68e+01 2.57e+01 4.42e+01</cell></row><row><cell>uk-2014-tpd</cell><cell cols="7">8.10e+01 5.31e+02 4.07e+02 2.56e+01 1.15e+02 3.04e+02 2.85e+02</cell><cell cols="7">3.59e+00 9.66e+00 9.92e+00 4.35e+00 9.66e+00 2.10e+01 2.16e+01</cell></row><row><cell>soc-Pokec</cell><cell cols="7">4.17e+01 1.34e+02 1.21e+02 3.04e+01 4.88e+01 1.00e+02 1.04e+02</cell><cell cols="7">1.96e+00 1.75e+01 3.91e+01 1.75e+01 1.75e+01 2.39e+01 2.45e+01</cell></row><row><cell>uk-2014-host</cell><cell cols="7">9.98e+02 4.68e+03 2.76e+03 8.90e+01 1.32e+03 2.89e+03 2.99e+03</cell><cell cols="7">1.81e+01 4.38e+01 6.80e+01 2.04e+01 4.38e+01 8.28e+01 8.73e+01</cell></row><row><cell cols="8">soc-LiveJournal1 9.08e+01 7.66e+02 6.24e+02 1.24e+02 1.24e+02 4.41e+02 4.49e+02</cell><cell cols="7">2.32e+00 2.20e+01 1.06e+02 2.20e+01 2.20e+01 4.49e+01 6.13e+01</cell></row><row><cell>enwiki-2013</cell><cell cols="7">8.36e+02 9.62e+02 7.09e+02 3.13e+01 9.77e+02 8.19e+02 8.38e+02</cell><cell cols="7">2.18e+01 7.58e+01 8.45e+01 7.58e+01 7.58e+01 2.14e+02 1.48e+02</cell></row><row><cell>uk-2002</cell><cell cols="7">1.47e+03 8.59e+03 5.17e+03 2.45e+02 1.73e+03 4.53e+03 5.29e+03</cell><cell cols="7">1.66e+01 8.65e+01 2.52e+02 8.65e+01 8.65e+01 7.87e+02 5.32e+02</cell></row><row><cell>arabic-2005</cell><cell cols="7">6.51e+03 7.64e+04 6.05e+04 6.08e+03 8.39e+03 3.59e+04 3.69e+04</cell><cell cols="7">1.98e+01 1.64e+02 4.80e+02 3.26e+02 1.64e+02 1.95e+03 1.40e+03</cell></row><row><cell>twitter-2010</cell><cell cols="7">1.21e+04 1.38e+05 1.31e+05 3.33e+04 1.99e+04 8.03e+04 7.65e+04</cell><cell cols="7">2.23e+02 1.23e+03 1.95e+03 1.23e+03 1.23e+03 2.22e+03 2.18e+03</cell></row><row><cell>sk-2005</cell><cell cols="7">5.52e+04 1.63e+05 1.29e+05 1.55e+04 5.23e+04 9.64e+04 8.42e+04</cell><cell cols="7">5.73e+01 2.94e+02 7.98e+02 2.94e+02 2.94e+02 5.83e+03 3.81e+03</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Table S4 :</head><label>S4</label><figDesc>Summary of networks used in scalability experiments with k-clique motifs. For each graph, we consider all edges as undirected.For several motifs, the motif adjacency matrix W M (Equation S19) has a simple formula in terms of the adjacency matrix of the original, directed, unweighted graph, G. Let A be the adjacency matrix for G and let U and B be the adjacency matrix of the unidirectional and</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="8">S3 Matrix-based interpretation of the motif-weighted adja-</cell></row><row><cell>cency matrix</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Network</cell><cell cols="2">description</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2"># nodes # edges</cell></row><row><cell>ego-Facebook</cell><cell cols="4">Facebook friendships</cell><cell></cell><cell>4.04K</cell><cell>88.2K</cell></row><row><cell>wiki-RfA</cell><cell cols="6">Adminship voting on Wikipedia 10.8K</cell><cell>182K</cell></row><row><cell>ca-AstroPh</cell><cell cols="4">author co-authorship</cell><cell></cell><cell>18.8K</cell><cell>198K</cell></row><row><cell>email-EuAll</cell><cell cols="5">Emails in a research institution</cell><cell>265K</cell><cell>364K</cell></row><row><cell>cit-HepPh</cell><cell cols="3">paper citations</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>34.5K</cell><cell>421K</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">soc-Slashdot0811 Slashdot user interactions</cell><cell></cell><cell>77.4K</cell><cell>469K</cell></row><row><cell>com-DBLP</cell><cell cols="4">author co-authorship</cell><cell></cell><cell>317K</cell><cell>1.05M</cell></row><row><cell>com-Youtube</cell><cell cols="3">User friendships</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">1.13M 2.99M</cell></row><row><cell>wiki-Talk</cell><cell cols="5">Wikipedia users interactions</cell><cell cols="2">2.39M 4.66M</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="5">Number of nodes in clique (k)</cell></row><row><cell>Network</cell><cell></cell><cell>4</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">ego-Facebook</cell><cell cols="3">14 317 6816</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>wiki-RfA</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">6 22</cell><cell>63</cell><cell cols="3">134 218 286</cell></row><row><cell>ca-AstroPh</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">5 35 285 2164</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>email-EuAll</cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>cit-HepPh</cell><cell></cell><cell>3</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>36</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">soc-Slashdot0811 3 12</cell><cell>55</cell><cell cols="3">282 1018 2836</cell></row><row><cell>com-DBLP</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">9 129 3234</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">com-Youtube</cell><cell cols="2">12 17</cell><cell>25</cell><cell>33</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>33</cell></row><row><cell>wiki-Talk</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">64 466 2898</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>S35</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>Table S5: Time to compute W M for k-clique motifs (seconds). Only computations that finished within two hours are listed.bidirectional links of G. Formally, B = A • A T and U = A − B, where • denotes the Hadamard (entry-wise) product. Table S6 lists the formula of W M for motifs M 1</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Infomap and the Louvain method are purely clustering methods in the sense that they take as input the graph and produce as output a set of labels for the nodes in the graph. In contrast to the spectral methods, we do not have control over the number of clusters. Also, only the spectral methods provide embeddings of the nodes into euclidean space, which is useful for S38 visualization. Thus, for our analysis of the transportation reachiability network in Section S6, we only compare spectral methods.S5 Details and comparison against existing methods for the C. elegans networkWe now provide more details on the cluster found for the C. elegans network of frontal neurons<ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(28)</ref>. In this network, the nodes are neurons and the edges are synapses. The net-</figDesc><table /><note>work data was downloaded from http://www.biological-networks.org/pubs/ suppl/celegans131.zip.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Table S7 :</head><label>S7</label><figDesc>Summary of Pearson correlations for spectral embeddings of the transportation reachability network. We list the 99% confidence interval for the Pearson correlation coefficient.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Primary spectral coordinate Secondary spectral coordinate</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">and metropolitan population and longitude</cell></row><row><cell>Embedding</cell><cell>99% confidence interval</cell><cell>99% confidence interval</cell></row><row><cell>Motif</cell><cell>0.43 ± 0.09</cell><cell>0.59 ± 0.08</cell></row><row><cell>Undirected</cell><cell>0.11 ± 0.12</cell><cell>0.39 ± 0.11</cell></row><row><cell>Undirected complement</cell><cell>0.31 ± 0.11</cell><cell>0.10 ± 0.12</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Coherent feedforward loops in the S. cerevisiae transcriptional regulation network In this network, each node is an operon (a group of genes in a mRNA molecule), and a directed edge from operon i to operon j means that i is regulated by a transcriptional factor encoded by j (29). Edges are directed and signed. A positive sign represents activation and a negative sign represents repression. The network data was downloaded from http://www.weizmann.ac.il/mcb/UriAlon/sites/mcb.UriAlon/files/uploads/NMpaper/yeastdata. mat and http://www.weizmann.ac.il/mcb/UriAlon/sites/mcb.UriAlon/files/ uploads/DownloadableData/list_of_ffls.pdf.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="6">was evaluated based on Adjusted Rand Index (ARI), F1 score, Normalized</cell></row><row><cell cols="8">Mutual Information (NMI), and Purity. In all cases, the motif-based methods have the best</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">performance.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="5">Evaluation Motif embedding Motif recursive Edge embedding Edge recursive</cell><cell>Infomap</cell><cell>Louvain</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>+ k-means</cell><cell cols="2">bi-partitioning + k-means</cell><cell>bi-partitioning</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Classification 1</cell><cell>ARI F1 NMI Purity</cell><cell>0.3005 0.4437 0.5040 0.5645</cell><cell>0.2156 0.3853 0.4468 0.5323</cell><cell>0.1564 0.3180 0.4112 0.4032</cell><cell>0.1226 0.2888 0.3879 0.4194</cell><cell>0.1423 0.3100 0.4035 0.4194</cell><cell>0.2207 0.4068 0.4220 0.5323</cell></row><row><cell>Classification 2</cell><cell>ARI F1 NMI Purity</cell><cell>0.3265 0.4802 0.4822 0.6129</cell><cell>0.2356 0.4214 0.4185 0.5806</cell><cell>0.1814 0.3550 0.3533 0.4839</cell><cell>0.1190 0.3035 0.3034 0.4355</cell><cell>0.1592 0.3416 0.3471 0.4677</cell><cell>0.2207 0.4068 0.4220 0.5323</cell></row><row><cell>S7.2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head>Table S11 :</head><label>S11</label><figDesc>Connected components of size greater than one for the motif adjacency matrix in the S. cerevisiae network for the coherent feedforward loop.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Size operons</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ALPHA1, CLN1, CLN2, GAL11, HO, MCM1, MFALPHA1, PHO5, SIN3,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>SPT16, STA1, STA2, STE3, STE6, SWI1, SWI4/SWI6, TUP1, SNF2/SWI1</cell></row><row><cell>9</cell><cell>HXT11, HXT9, IPT1, PDR1, PDR3, PDR5, SNQ2, YOR1, YRR1</cell></row><row><cell>9</cell><cell>GCN4, ILV1, ILV2, ILV5, LEU3, LEU4, MET16, MET17, MET4</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>CHO1, CHO2, INO2, INO2/INO4, OPI3, UME6</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>DAL80, DAL80/GZF3, GAP1, GAT1, GLN1, GLN3</cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>CYC1, GAL1, GAL4, MIG1, HAP2/3/4/5</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>ADH2, CCR4, SPT6</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>CDC19, RAP1, REB1</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>DIT1, IME1, RIM101</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Motif M 6 in the English Wikipedia article network The English Wikipedia network (57-59) consists of 4.21 million nodes (representing articles)</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Motif nodes</cell><cell>Function</cell><cell>Class label</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="4">Motif-based Edge-based Infomap Louvain</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">GAL11 ALPHA1</cell><cell cols="2">MFALPHA1 pheromone response</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>-1</cell></row><row><cell>GCN4</cell><cell>MET4</cell><cell>MET16</cell><cell>Metionine biosynthesis</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>-1</cell></row><row><cell>GCN4</cell><cell>MET4</cell><cell>MET17</cell><cell>Metionine biosynthesis</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>-1</cell></row><row><cell>GCN4</cell><cell>LEU3</cell><cell>ILV1</cell><cell>Leucine and branched amino acid biosynthesis</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>GCN4</cell><cell>LEU3</cell><cell>ILV2</cell><cell>Leucine and branched amino acid biosynthesis</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>GCN4</cell><cell>LEU3</cell><cell>ILV5</cell><cell>Leucine and branched amino acid biosynthesis</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>GCN4</cell><cell>LEU3</cell><cell>LEU4</cell><cell>Leucine and branched amino acid biosynthesis</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>GLN3</cell><cell>GAT1</cell><cell>GAP1</cell><cell>Nitrogen utilization</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>GLN3</cell><cell>GAT1</cell><cell>DAL80</cell><cell>Nitrogen utilization</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>GLN3</cell><cell>GAT1</cell><cell cols="2">DAL80/GZF3 Glutamate synthetase</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>GLN3</cell><cell>GAT1</cell><cell>GLN1</cell><cell>Glutamate synthetase</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>MIG1</cell><cell cols="2">HAP2/3/4/5 CYC1</cell><cell>formation of apocytochromes</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>-1</cell></row><row><cell>MIG1</cell><cell>GAL4</cell><cell>GAL1</cell><cell>Galactokinase</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>-1</cell></row><row><cell>PDR1</cell><cell>YRR1</cell><cell>SNQ2</cell><cell>Drug resistance</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>PDR1</cell><cell>YRR1</cell><cell>YOR1</cell><cell>Drug resistance</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>PDR1</cell><cell>PDR3</cell><cell>HXT11</cell><cell>Drug resistance</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>PDR1</cell><cell>PDR3</cell><cell>HXT9</cell><cell>Drug resistance</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>PDR1</cell><cell>PDR3</cell><cell>PDR5</cell><cell>Drug resistance</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>PDR1</cell><cell>PDR3</cell><cell>IPT1</cell><cell>Drug resistance</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>PDR1</cell><cell>PDR3</cell><cell>SNQ2</cell><cell>Drug resistance</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>PDR1</cell><cell>PDR3</cell><cell>YOR1</cell><cell>Drug resistance</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">RIM101 IME1</cell><cell>DIT1</cell><cell>sporulation-specific</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>SPT16</cell><cell cols="2">SWI4/SWI6 CLN1</cell><cell>Cell cycle and mating type switch</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>SPT16</cell><cell cols="2">SWI4/SWI6 CLN2</cell><cell>Cell cycle and mating type switch</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>SPT16</cell><cell cols="2">SWI4/SWI6 HO</cell><cell>Cell cycle and mating type switch</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>-1</cell></row><row><cell>TUP1</cell><cell>ALPHA1</cell><cell cols="2">MFALPHA1 Mating factor alpha</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>-1</cell><cell>5</cell></row><row><cell>UME6</cell><cell cols="2">INO2/INO4 CHO1</cell><cell>Phospholipid biosynthesis</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>UME6</cell><cell cols="2">INO2/INO4 CHO2</cell><cell>Phospholipid biosynthesis</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>UME6</cell><cell cols="2">INO2/INO4 OPI3</cell><cell>Phospholipid biosynthesis</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>Frac. coherently labeled</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>29 / 29</cell><cell>25 / 29</cell><cell>23 / 29</cell><cell>23 / 29</cell></row><row><cell>Accuracy</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>0.97</cell><cell>0.82</cell><cell>0.68</cell><cell>0.76</cell></row><row><cell>S7.3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" />			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Milo</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">298</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">824</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mangan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zaslaver</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Alon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of molecular biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">334</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">197</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Leskovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the IEEE</title>
		<meeting>the IEEE</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1892</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Holland</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Leinhardt</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">American Journal of Sociology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="492" to="513" />
			<date type="published" when="1970" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rosvall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Esquivel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Lancichinetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lambiotte</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Pržulj</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Corneil</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Jurisica</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3508</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Leskovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dasgupta</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Mahoney</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Internet Mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">29</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ö</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Yaveroglu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Scientific reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Mangan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Alon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">100</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">11980</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Honey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kötter</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Breakspear</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Sporns</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">104</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10240</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Schaeffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Science Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">27</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Minimizing φ M (S) is NP-hard, which follows from the NP-hardness of the traditional definition of conductance</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">See the Supplementary Material</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Formally, when the motif has three nodes, the selected cluster S satisfies φ M (S) ≤ 4 φ * M ≤ 1, where φ * M is the smallest motif conductance of any possible node set S</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">The normalized motif Laplacian matrix is L M = D −1/2 (D − W M )D −1/2 , where D is a diagonal matrix with the row-sums of W M on the diagonal (D ii = j (W M ) ij )</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>and D −1/2 is the same matrix with the inverse square-roots on the diagonal (D</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The spectral ordering σ is the by-value ordering of D −1/2 z, where z is the eigenvector corresponding to the second</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>smallest eigenvalue of L M , i.e., σ i is the index of D −1/2 z with the ith smallest value</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Seshadhri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Pinar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Kolda</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Statistical Analysis and Data Mining</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Andersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Lang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 47th Annual IEEE Symposium on Foundations of Computer Science</title>
		<meeting>the 47th Annual IEEE Symposium on Foundations of Computer Science</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="475" to="486" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Whang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Dhillon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Gleich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">SIAM Data Mining</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename><surname>Ng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">I</forename><surname>Jordan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Weiss</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="849" to="856" />
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Boley</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">325</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Riddle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Blumenthal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Meyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">C. elegans II</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1997" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>second edn</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature neuroscience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">107</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Frey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Dueck</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">315</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">972</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Serrour</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Arenas</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Gómez</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computer Communications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">629</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Michoel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Joshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Nachtergaele</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Van De Peer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Molecular BioSystems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2769</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Benson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Gleich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Leskovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">SIAM Data Mining</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Krzakala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">110</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">20935</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kaiser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Hilgetag</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Computational Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">95</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Alon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature Reviews Genetics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">450</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Sporns</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kötter</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Biology</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">369</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Inokuchi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Washio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Motoda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Principles of Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="23" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of ICCM (Citeseer, 2007)</title>
		<meeting>ICCM (Citeseer, 2007)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">378</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">O</forename><surname>Gharan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Trevisan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Journal of the ACM</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">61</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">37</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Annals of Combinatorics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Boley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Ranjan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z.-L</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Linear Algebra and its Applications</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">435</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">224</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Malliaros</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Vazirgiannis</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Physics Reports</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">533</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">95</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b37">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Very Large Scale Integration (VLSI) Systems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Karypis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Aggarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Shekhar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE Transactions on</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">69</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b38">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Agarwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Branson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Belongie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 23rd International Conference on Machine Learning</title>
		<meeting>the 23rd International Conference on Machine Learning</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="17" to="24" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b39">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Huang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Schölkopf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1601" to="1608" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b40">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Linear and Multilinear Algebra</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Rodríguez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">71</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b41">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Lecture notes on expansion, sparsest cut, and spectral graph theory</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Trevisan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://www.eecs.berkeley.edu/˜luca/books/expanders.pdf.Accessed" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-06-28" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b42">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Demeyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PloS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">61183</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b43">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Houbraken</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS ONE</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">97896</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b44">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wernicke</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Computational Biology and Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">347</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b45">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Wernicke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Rasche</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1152</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b46">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Aberger</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nötzli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Olukotun</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Ré</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="arXiv">arXiv:1503.02368</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">arXiv preprint</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b47">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Latapy</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Theoretical Computer Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">407</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">458</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b48">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Berry</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 5th Conference on Innovations in Theoretical Computer Science</title>
		<meeting>the 5th Conference on Innovations in Theoretical Computer Science<address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="234" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b49">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Marcus</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Shavitt</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">IEEE 30th International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems Workshops</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="92" to="98" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b50">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Chiba</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Nishizeki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">SIAM Journal on Computing</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">14</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">210</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b51">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Schank</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Experimental and Efficient Algorithms</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="606" to="609" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b52">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Becchetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Boldi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Castillo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Gionis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 14th ACM SIGKDD international conference on Knowledge discovery and data mining</title>
		<meeting>the 14th ACM SIGKDD international conference on Knowledge discovery and data mining</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="24" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b53">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Cohen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Computing in Science &amp; Engineering</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">72</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b54">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Parlett</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">The Symmetric Eigenvalue Problem</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>SIAM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b55">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Applied Parallel Computing Industrial Computation and Optimization</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Maschhoff</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Sorensen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="478" to="486" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b56">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Leskovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Krevl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Datasets</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://snap.stanford.edu/data" />
		<title level="m">Stanford large network dataset collection</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b57">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Boldi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Codenotti</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Santini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vigna</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Software: Practice and Experience</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">34</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">711</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b58">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Boldi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vigna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 13th International Conference on World Wide Web</title>
		<meeting>the 13th International Conference on World Wide Web</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="595" to="602" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b59">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Boldi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rosa</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Santini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vigna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 20th International Conference on World Wide Web</title>
		<meeting>the 20th International Conference on World Wide Web</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="587" to="596" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b60">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Boldi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Marino</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Santini</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Vigna</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the companion publication of the 23rd international conference on World wide web companion (International World Wide Web Conferences Steering Committee</title>
		<meeting>the companion publication of the 23rd international conference on World wide web companion (International World Wide Web Conferences Steering Committee</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="227" to="228" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b61">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Azad</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Buluç</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Gilbert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the IPDPSW, Workshop on Graph Algorithm Building Blocks (GABB) (2015)</title>
		<meeting>the IPDPSW, Workshop on Graph Algorithm Building Blocks (GABB) (2015)</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="804" to="811" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b62">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rosvall</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Bergstrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1118</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b63">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Journal of statistical mechanics: theory and experiment</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Blondel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J.-L</forename><surname>Guillaume</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lambiotte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Lefebvre</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<biblScope unit="page">10008</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b64">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Trophic Dynamics in South Florida Ecosystem, FY 97: The Florida Bay Ecosystem</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Ulanowicz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Bondavalli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Egnotovich</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<pubPlace>Solomons, MD</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Chesapeake Biological Laboratory</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Tech. Rep. CBL 98-123</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b65">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bascompte</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Melián</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Sala</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</title>
		<meeting>the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5443</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b66">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bascompte</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">325</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">416</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b67">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Stouffer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Camacho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A N</forename><surname>Amaral</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Proceedings of the Royal Society of London B: Biological Sciences</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">274</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1931</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b68">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Wagner</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 18th International Symposium on Mathematical Foundations of Computer Science</title>
		<meeting>the 18th International Symposium on Mathematical Foundations of Computer Science</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="744" to="750" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b69">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Manning</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Raghavan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Schütze</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Introduction to Information Retrieval</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<publisher>Cambridge university press Cambridge</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b70">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Dobrin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Q</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Beg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A.-L</forename><surname>Barabási</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Oltvai</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC bioinformatics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">10</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b71">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kwak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Park</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Moon</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 19th International Conference on World Wide Web</title>
		<meeting>the 19th International Conference on World Wide Web</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="591" to="600" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b72">
	<analytic>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chakraborty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Ganguly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mukherjee</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Advances in Social Networks Analysis and Mining (ASONAM)</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="130" to="137" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b73">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Leskovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kleinberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Faloutsos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transactions on Knowledge Discovery from Data (TKDD)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b74">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>West</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Paskov</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Leskovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Potts</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transactions of the Association for Computational Linguistics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">297</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b75">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Leskovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kleinberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Faloutsos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the eleventh ACM SIGKDD international conference on Knowledge discovery in data mining</title>
		<meeting>the eleventh ACM SIGKDD international conference on Knowledge discovery in data mining</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="177" to="187" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b76">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Gehrke</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Ginsparg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kleinberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM SIGKDD Explorations Newsletter</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">149</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b77">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Albert</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Jeong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A.-L</forename><surname>Barabási</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Nature</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">401</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">130</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b78">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Leskovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Adamic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Huberman</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ACM Transactions on the Web (TWEB)</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b79">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Leskovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Huttenlocher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Kleinberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">ICWSM</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b80">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Leskovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mcauley</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Advances in neural information processing systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="539" to="547" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b81">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Takac</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zabovsky</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">International Scientific Conference and International Workshop Present Day Trends of Innovations</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="6" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b82">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Backstrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Huttenlocher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Kleinberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Lan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the 12th ACM SIGKDD international conference on Knowledge discovery and data mining</title>
		<meeting>the 12th ACM SIGKDD international conference on Knowledge discovery and data mining</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="44" to="54" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b83">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Leskovec</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">IEEE 12th International Conference on Data Mining</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>IEEE</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="745" to="754" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
